<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: screencast | jasonwryan.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/categories/screencast/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jasonwryan.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-01-13T20:49:41+13:00</updated>
  <id>http://jasonwryan.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jason Ryan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Vimprobable Walkthrough]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2012/11/20/vimprobable/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-20T18:58:00+13:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2012/11/20/vimprobable</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/post_images/vimprobable-logo.png" title="&lsquo;Vimprobable logo&rsquo;" >
I have written about <a href="http://vimprobable.org" title="Vimprobable homepage">Vimprobable</a>
a couple of times over the last two years<sup>1</sup>,
it is one of those projects that, for a variety of reasons, I have picked up
and stuck with.  Like <a href="http://dwm.suckless.org" title="dwm homepage">dwm</a>,
<a href="http://vim.org" title="Vim homepage">Vim</a> and
<a href="http://tmux.sourceforge.net/" title="tmux homepage">tmux</a>,
it is an essential part of my working environment and is installed on all of my
machines, where it is my default browser. It&rsquo;s simplicity, power and
configurability are why, despite looking at a few other similar projects, I
have stuck with Vimprobable since first installing it.</p>

<p>After my last post, a <a href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2012/09/28/screencast/" title="An intro to dwm">dwm screencast</a>,
I wanted to have another crack at making a decent screencast. Sadly,
this is not it.  I can say that making a <em>good</em> screencast is not a simple
accomplishment; there are so many elements that require significant attention. I
spent a good many hours this time around playing with custom Xorg modelines,
<code>ffmpeg</code>&rsquo;s arcane encoding options and, to be frank, the final product is just not worth
all that effort.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m going to stick with plain text from now on. It requires little more from me
than a passing acquaintance with the subject matter, some loosely held and
<a href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2012/08/18/trolls/" title="Trolling Arch Linux">firmly expressed opinions</a>
and my unbridled confidence in the fact that anyone who
has read this far down the page is so bereft of other, more pressing things to
think about that they may inadvertently find a scintilla of amusement in here…</p>

<p>With that explanation out of the way, I give you my final screencast:</p>

<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/53829053?byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;badge=0&amp;color=ffffff" 
width="350" height="197" frameborder="0" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p></p>

<p><a href="http://vimeo.com/53829053">An Introduction to Vimprobable</a> on 
<a href="http://vimeo.com">Vimeo</a>.</p>


<h4>Notes</h4>

<ol>
<li>First back in <a href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2010/10/07/vimprobable/">October, 2010</a> and then,
more recently, in <a href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2011/06/26/using-vimprobable/">June, 2011</a>.</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A dwm Screencast]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2012/09/28/screencast/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-28T09:18:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2012/09/28/screencast</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/post_images/dwm-logo.png" title="&lsquo;dwm logo&rsquo;" >
Over the last week as I have been at home convalescing I have, quite unaccountably,
found myself watching videos of tiling window managers. In all, I have probably watched
between twenty and thirty of these videos so I feel, quite confidently, that I have a
firm grasp of what constitutes the genre. Consequently, I also feel that I can&mdash;based
on the range of the material I have reviewed, and the scrutiny and attention therein
applied&mdash;share an unequivocal judgement as to the overall quality of the genre: it
sucks.</p>

<p>Moreover, these videos invariably suck in the same couple of ways; they always lack
any sort of narration, which means that you are stuck silently watching some sort of
paroxysm of window rearrangement without <em>any</em> context or explanation, as if the fact
that you can inflict this sort of injury on an X display is rationale enough. And,
secondly, just as frequently, they feature a cursor being dragged around the screen
doing the damage; using the mouse to demonstrate the capabilities of a tiling window
manager is the sort of vestigial behaviour more commonly associated with pagan
superstition or mild enfeeblement…</p>

<p>Rather that simply bask in the sense of superiority that these observations have
afforded me, I thought that I would make my own, more lasting, contribution to the
canon. I can only describe this process as instructive.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GQ5s6T25jCc"><img class="center" src="/images/post_images/tower.jpg" title="dwm screencast" ></a></p>

<p>The best that can be said of this video is that, while it sucks just as hard as the others
that I have reviewed over the past week, it has the distinguishing feature of at least
sucking <em>differently</em>. For example, it has an audio track, so in theory the actions on the
screen should be accompanied by the narrator&rsquo;s soothing tones. Sadly, this is not the case.
The crappy quality of my headset, my hoarse throat, and most egregiously, my decision to eschew
post production and shoot it in one take means that the audio is poorly recorded, and at times
literally inarticulate, rambling.</p>

<p>If nothing else, the exercise has taught me to really appreciate the work of people who
do this thing well; Drew Neil&rsquo;s excellent
<a href="http://vimcasts.org/" title="The Vimcasts homepage">Vimcasts</a> being a case in point.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
