<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: media | jasonwryan.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/categories/media/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-05-27T20:21:20+12:00</updated>
  <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jason Ryan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Delicious? Not after the first bite…]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2011/09/28/delicious/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-28T09:27:00+13:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2011/09/28/delicious</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/261312/Blog-images/delicious1.png" alt="image" /></p>

<p>I have used
<a href="http://delicious.com" title="Once great social bookmarking site...">delicious</a>,
the bookmarking service, for just on five years now and over that time
added around 1500 bookmarks. This suggests to me that I am a heavy, but
not compulsive boomarker—I tend to only add pages that I think I will
have a reasonably good chance of wanting to reference in the future.</p>

<p>I am (or rather, was) an unabashed fan of the service. To the point
where earlier this year I wrote
<a href="http://anonscm.debian.org/gitweb/?p=surfraw/surfraw.git;a=blob_plain;f=elvi/deli;hb=8e32f5edaf26b7a65e5535d81b513f6d63e82847" title="Elvis in the Surfraw CVS tree">a Surfraw elvis to search the site</a>.
As this would suggest, I use the site frequently, not just to bookmark
or retrieve my own pages, but to search for other pages that people have
considered “bookmark-worthy” (which is generally a pretty good indicator
of quality).</p>

<p>Like many comitted users, when the news leaked out late last year that
<a href="http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/rip_delicious_you_were_so_beautiful_to_me.php" title="RWW">Yahoo was shuttering delicious</a>,
I jumped to Pinboard and have been
<a href="http://pinboard.in/u:jasonwryan/" title="My boomarks on Pinboard">synching my bookmarks</a>
between the two sites since. In retrospect, that turned out to be an
excellent decision.</p>

<p>The “new” delicious was launched overnight and I think it is fair to say
that it has been completely and utterly eviscerated. It has gone from
being a site that served a very specific (and incredibly useful)
purpose—saving and tagging web pages for future use—to a bland,
lowest-common-denominator, generic “social” site, like countless others
that have arrived and disappeared with quirky names like Plurk, Plonker,
etc..</p>

<p>The site <em>looks good</em>; all light and airy and spacious (that space will,
I am sure, be quickly filled with advertising), but they have stripped
all the utility from the site. You can no longer actually access and
manage your bookmarks. It is a colossal failure.</p>

<p>I have 757 tags. I know that tag clouds are considered old hat, but on a
site built on taxonomies, they are still an incredibly effective way of
presenting information. The new delicious has dispensed with them. They
have also decided that I don’t need to see all of my tags, so I can now
only view 50 of them. <strong>Fifty out of seven hundred and fifty</strong>.
Presumably I am expected to guess all the rest…</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/261312/Blog-images/delicious2.png" alt="image" /></p>

<p><sup>The new tag display on the left and the old, as a cloud, on the right.</sup></p>

<p>These aren’t options, though. All of the settings to display tags, tag
bundles, etc., and the options to edit tags have been removed. You can’t
access any of the tools to manage your bookmarks. The designers have
decreed that you can no longer manage your information in a useful way.
Morons.</p>

<p>The clueless mediocrities responsible for this will probably think that
they are reinventing the site and making it relevant for a broader, less
geeky market. And they are probably right. The fact that the site looks
remarkably like a phone app suggests that sort of studied rush to the
bottom.</p>

<p>What they have done is something of an achievement on one level, though.
They have made Yahoo look good. In all the time that Yahoo owned
delicious, they were only able to neglect it; these new clowns have
completely fscked it…</p>

<p>If you bookmark sites because you are semi-intelligent and you recognize
that being able to easily access and manage information effectively is
critical to your intellectual and social wellbeing, then head over to
<a href="http://pinboard.in/" title="A real boomarking site">Pinboard</a> and sign up
now.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quora's Quandary]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2011/05/28/quoras-quandary/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-28T10:05:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2011/05/28/quoras-quandary</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/261312/Blog-images/quora1.png" alt="image" /></p>

<p>I joined <a href="http://www.quora.com/" title="Quora: Q&amp;A site">Quora</a> early in the
new year and, while
<a href="http://techcrunch.com/2011/01/23/why-i-don%E2%80%99t-buy-the-quora-hype/" title="TC article on the hype">the hype has in no way abated</a>,
I have found that increasingly over the months that I have been
visiting, there is less and less reason for me to return on any regular
basis. And this puzzles me as I think the concept is, for me, an
attractive one.</p>

<p>In the five-odd months I have been visiting the site, I have managed to
<a href="http://www.quora.com/Jason-Ryan" title="My Quora profile">contribute 58 answers</a>
and over one hundred edits (more on that below); this strikes me as a reasonable
commitment on my part and one that should return some dividend to me –
at least in terms of satisfaction with the site. Alas, no.</p>

<p>And why not? For several reasons. And reasons that have only really
become apparent over the last month as I started to spend time on the
<a href="http://unix.stackexchange.com/" title="Unix and Linux Stack Exchange">Unix &amp; Linux Stack Exchange site</a>.
The contrast between the <em>experience</em> of the two sites, that are in
essence very similar, couldn’t be more striking.</p>

<p>The primary difference between the two is that Unix.SE isn’t a social
site: you don’t follow anyone. Which, when you think about Q&amp;A sites,
makes a lot more sense than Quora’s model. I still don’t understand the
point of following people on Quora. Perhaps I am not following enough
people, or the wrong ones, but I have yet to see <em>any benefit</em> in
following on the site.</p>

<p>One other area of seeming similarity between the sites is the ability to
vote up (or down) questions and answers. On Unix.SE, this is implemented
as a real strength as these votes determine contributor’s reputation,
described thus:</p>

<blockquote><p>Reputation is a rough measurement of how much the community trusts
you. Reputation is never given, it is earned by convincing fellow
users that you know what you’re talking about.</p></blockquote>

<p>This has a twofold effect: it motivates contributors to provide quality
answers (and
<a href="http://unix.stackexchange.com/badges" title="StackExchange badges">rewards</a>
them when they do), and more importantly, gives you a heuristic for how
credible an answer may be. Quora doesn’t have this concept and, for me,
is much the poorer for it.</p>

<p>Reputation has consequences on Unix.SE: the more you accrue, the more
privileges on the site you are granted. Again, this builds the
community’s capability while encouraging individual contributors.</p>

<p>Some of the other areas where Quora is really left wanting in comparison
to Unix.SE are around the design of the site. The text box where you
enter your answers or edits is a case in point:</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/261312/Blog-images/quora2.png" alt="image" /></p>

<p>On Quora, it is like trying to change a car battery through a letterbox.
The single, overriding impression is that entering information into the
site is neither a priority nor pleasurable which, for a site aspiring to
be a knowledge repository is incredibly perverse.</p>

<p>This is compounded by the fact that the tools for presenting the
information that you want to add to the site can charitably be described
as rudimentary (one of the reasons that I have 100-odd edits is that it
takes at least two to three attempts to present information in a
semi-acceptable fashion). Searching for
“<a href="http://www.quora.com/Quora-product/Are-there-any-markup-tags-when-writing-a-question?q=quora+markup+tools" title="Recursion alert">quora markup tools</a>”
is as disappointing as it is frustrating.</p>

<p>Being able to present information appropriately is critical. The
StackExchange sites
<a href="http://unix.stackexchange.com/editing-help" title="Unix.SE editing guidleines">allow all sorts</a>
of HTML tags and
<a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/syntax" title="markdown syntax">markdown</a>,
without apparently any additional
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cross-site_scripting" title="Wikipedia page on Cross site scripting">XSS risk</a><sup>1</sup>.
The result is questions and answers that are formatted in a way that
enhances their legibility, rather than detracting from it.</p>

<p>There are some other areas where Quora is not measuring up for me:
opaque editorial and moderation policies and practices and an
unwillingness to more actively curate the questions – and no, those two
statements are not contradictory.</p>

<p>The overall impression I am left with is that while both sites have
similar aims (albeit Unix.SE’s is much more specific in terms of the
subject matter), Quora seems to me to be really failing at building a
community around it. Unless, of course, you count social media experts…</p>

<h5>Notes</h5>

<ol>
<li>God knows if that is actually the reason they refuse to allow
potential contributors the ability to adequately format their
information, but it seems plausible enough.</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vapourware]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2010/04/03/vapourware/"/>
    <updated>2010-04-03T13:18:00+13:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2010/04/03/vapourware</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This morning I received a heap of brochures inviting me to attend
professional development courses, training seminars and conferences. One
in particular stood out for reasons I’d like to share with you.</p>

<p>By way of context; it’s a 2 day programme (workshops on the first,
plenary sessions on the second) of social media for internal
communicators. As I have a keen interest in internal communications, I
studied their offering.</p>

<p>One presentation, from an “international guest speaker,” is so striking
I’ll reprint it in its entirety, removing the name of the company to
prevent them any (further) embarassment, (all emphasis mine):</p>

<blockquote><p>[Multi-national company] is rolling out Sharepoint this year. It
<strong>will</strong> provide the organization with an enhanced way of
communicating, collaborating and managing content - a dynamic platform
on which to evolve and further improve [company’s] way or working.
From an internal communications perspective, the Microsoft Office
product provides an <strong>updated way</strong> to engage colleagues, in order to
drive winning culture and business performance. This session captures
the opportunities, benefits, <strong>and realities</strong> of implementing and
living with Sharepoint.</p>

<p>[Employee name], Internal Communications Director, [company].</p></blockquote>

<p>Did I read that correctly? The company haven’t actually implemented the
technology yet, but they are still fronting someone to sell it’s future
virtues.</p>

<p>Whether or not the technology is able to deliver these benefits (and I
<a href="http://twitter.com/jasonwryan/status/839079414">doubt it</a> <a href="http://twitter.com/jasonwryan/status/839079197">very
much</a>), shouldn’t the
corporate communicator at least be talking about, oh let’s say for a
whim, something <em>grounded in evidence?</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
