<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[jasonwryan.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-22T17:17:10+12:00</updated>
  <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jason Ryan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Asking for Help]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2013/06/15/asking/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-15T10:39:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2013/06/15/asking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/261312/Blog-images/bowl.jpg" title="'Flickr image of Begging Bowl'" >
Another great peristaltic movement in Arch&#8217;s rolling release digestive system
happened over the last couple of weeks, the move of all binaries
<a href="https://www.archlinux.org/news/binaries-move-to-usrbin-requiring-update-intervention/" title="Arch News update">to /usr/bin</a>.
This move had been foreshadowed for several months and, despite announcements
on the front page of the Arch website, the mailing lists and the release going
through [testing] and the resulting thread on the forums, there was still a
surprising amount of carnage<sup>1</sup> in it&#8217;s wake.</p>

<p>In the aftermath (although I expect that it will take some months for it to
completely pass through the system), what struck me was not so much the variety
and ingenuity of the ways people had managed to break their installs<sup>2</sup>
as how they approached the community seeking help afterwards.</p>

<p>There are already some fine guides on how to do this, notably
ESR&#8217;s <a href="http://www.catb.org/esr/faqs/smart-questions.html" title="Just read it…">How to ask Questions the Smart Way</a>
and—specifically for Arch—zendeavour&#8217;s
<a href="http://redd.it/tjjwr" title="On Reddit">troubleshooting for newcomers</a>;
this isn&#8217;t an attempt to add or expand on that genre. Rather, it is
a look at a subset of attitudes that some people adopt<sup>3</sup>
as they seek the assistance of the community.</p>

<p>The first is the <strong>blamer</strong>. The proponent of the  “all-guns-blazing” approach.
I&#8217;ll paraphrase, but there are enough examples on the boards to illustrate the
point: “my system can&#8217;t boot, it&#8217;s not my fault and I am here to let you know
that I am unhappy and demand recourse.” This is, unquestionably, the most
puzzling of all the strategies. It is often coupled with the (sadly almost
always empty) threat to abandon the distro and it&#8217;s apparently beleaguered
community.</p>

<p>Puzzling because I have yet to encounter a single situation in life, online
or off, where opening with hostility and blame is an intelligent approach to
seeking assistance. If you are going to adopt this approach, please supersize
to “rage quit” and expend your energy actually delivering on your threat.</p>

<p>The next is the <strong>wheedler</strong>. Less objectionable than the incendiary approach,
it is nonetheless similarly ineffective. Wheedlers are distinguished by
peppering their posts liberally with declarations of their ineptitude and
“noobness”, in the mistaken belief that this will engender a wave of sympathy
prior to soothing hand-holding and spoon-feeding. There is a strong correlation
between this behaviour and the various types of
<a href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2012/03/17/vampires/" title="Post on the taxonomy of vampires">help vampirism</a>.</p>

<p>Wheedling won&#8217;t lead to quicker, or more informed, advice and assistance; in
all likelihood it will just discourage others from helping because
they can see that rewarding this sort of behaviour has a longer-term
deleterious impact on the health of the community.</p>

<p>Then there is the <strong>Vulcan</strong>. A curiosity more than an annoyance, these
people seem to inhabit some sort of adolescent fantasy land where the Internet
is a venue for them to revel in their almost superhero-like powers of technical
<em>awesomeness</em>; said powers manifesting to others as a sort of benign
cluelessness.</p>

<p>Their posts are invariably brief and completely devoid of relevant detail to the
point of cryptic because, “hey, we all <em>know</em> what this issue is,” and are
littered with smilies and that stupid emoticon with the sunglasses. Rather than
actually describing their problem, they want people to think that, by a process
of <a href="http://en.memory-alpha.org/wiki/Vulcan_mind_meld" title="There is a Star Trek wiki?">mind-melding</a>,
other “hackers” will intuit the subtle depth and intricacy of the issue and
then type out a detailed step-by-step guide of how to solve it.</p>

<p>Finally, there is the <strong>conspiracist</strong>. These malcontents see every
significant change in Arch as being part of a wider agenda to corrupt the purity
of the UNIX® philosophy. They also tend to blame
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lennart_Poettering" title="Lennarts wikipedia page">Lennart Poettering</a>
for <em>everything</em>. These unfortunates are clearly already suffering such mental anguish
trying to reconcile their obsessiveness about the past with a rolling
release that they deserve our pity more than our contempt (but I am equally
happy providing either)…</p>

<p>As I said, these are fortunately just a subset and very much represent the
minority of attitudes.  The vast majority tend to be aware that, at
one time or another, <em>everyone</em> will need some help to solve a problem.
Therefore it is best to approach it in a matter-of-fact way, using the practical
guidance on asking questions on a technical forum, and with a degree of humility
and a willingness to learn from the people who are prepared to share their
knowledge and experience.</p>

<h4>Notes</h4>

<ol>
<li>Where “carnage” should be understood as a minor PEBKAC epidemia…</li>
<li>From shutting down mid-update (because a reboot fixes <em>everything</em>) to
still using <code>consolekit</code>, <code>initscripts</code> and <code>grub-legacy</code>: all deprecated some time
ago.</li>
<li>I resisted linking to specific posts on the boards to provide actual examples,
the more motivated among you will find them without difficulty.</li>
</ol>


<p>Flickr Creative Commons image by
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/buddhist_fox/4795942625/">Buddhist Fox</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
