<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: backup | jasonwryan.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/categories/backup/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-05-12T17:41:46+12:00</updated>
  <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jason Ryan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tarsnap]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2011/09/08/tarsnap/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-08T17:55:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2011/09/08/tarsnap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/261312/Blog-images/tarsnap.jpg" alt="image" /></p>

<p>I have been using <a href="http://www.tarsnap.com/" title="Tarsnap homepage">Tarsnap</a>
for a couple of months now to backup
<a href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2010/10/04/the-setup/" title="My setup">my EeePC</a>.
Tarsnap’s (superb) tagline is: <code>online backups for the truly paranoid.</code></p>

<p>Essentially, Tarsnap stores your encrypted backups on
<a href="http://aws.amazon.com/s3//192-5766046-6455343/" title="Amazon page">Amazon’s S3 servers</a>,
recognizes duplicate data and avoids storing it again, and only deletes
data once no remaining archives require it. I can recommend it as a
terrific service for a number of reasons.</p>

<p>It is <em><a href="http://www.tarsnap.com/security.html" title="Security page">secure</a></em>.
Developed by the FreeBSD Security Officer, there is a
<a href="http://www.tarsnap.com/bugbounty.html" title="Bug bounty details">bug bounty</a> for
anyone who does discover bugs or security holes. It is very reasonably
priced. It is reliable. And most importantly,
<a href="http://www.tarsnap.com/about.html" title="Tarsnap about page">Dr Colin Percival</a>,
erstwhile child prodigy and developer, is extremely helpful either on
the mailing list or IRC if you have any questions or need help.</p>

<p>If, however, you have a quick look at the
<a href="http://www.tarsnap.com/man-tarsnap.1.html" title="tarsnap(1)">man page</a>, you will
see that it is not exactly a simple application. After a couple of
months of trying to remember all of the relevant flags, I searched for a
script that would simplify the process for me. There are
<a href="http://duckduckgo.com/?q=tarsnap+%2B+bash+script" title="DDG results">a few online</a>,
but they are all intended to fully automate the process (which makes
sense for something like backups)…</p>

<p>What I was looking for, however, was something more interactive: more
along the lines of a prompt. So, realizing I would have to scratch my
own itch, I wrote a wrapper script to assist my failing memory.</p>

<p>The script prints out a menu of the available options and, once you have
selected the activity that you would like (creating a new snapshot,
deleting an old one etc.,), then the script checks if any further input
is required, for example, the name of the snapshot to delete, and then
executes it. It is nothing flash, but it works…</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/261312/Blog-images/tarsnap2.png" alt="image" /></p>

<p>You can <a href="https://bitbucket.org/jasonwryan/eeepc/src/241da582a0fd/Scripts/snap" title="Snap script in mercurial repo">grab the script</a>
from my mercurial repo. It’s written in bash, but if you require
<a href="http://tldp.org/LDP/abs/html/portabilityissues.html" title="Advanced Bash Scripting Guide">portability</a>,
it shouldn’t be too hard to tweak.</p>

<h4>Updated 3/10/11</h4>

<p>I have rewritten the script to be
<a href="http://pubs.opengroup.org/onlinepubs/9699919799/" title="POSIX Standard at the Open Group">POSIX compliant</a>
and also to better conform to basic UNIX behaviours, in terms of the
options etc. It should now be good to run in most shells.</p>

<h5>Notes</h5>

<p>Creative Commons licensed image by
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/declanjewell/2447653142/" title="Flickr image credit">Declan TM</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
