<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: bullshit | jasonwryan.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/categories/bullshit/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-03-27T22:24:43+13:00</updated>
  <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jason Ryan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vapourware]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2010/04/03/vapourware/"/>
    <updated>2010-04-03T13:18:00+13:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2010/04/03/vapourware</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This morning I received a heap of brochures inviting me to attend
professional development courses, training seminars and conferences. One
in particular stood out for reasons I’d like to share with you.</p>

<p>By way of context; it’s a 2 day programme (workshops on the first,
plenary sessions on the second) of social media for internal
communicators. As I have a keen interest in internal communications, I
studied their offering.</p>

<p>One presentation, from an “international guest speaker,” is so striking
I’ll reprint it in its entirety, removing the name of the company to
prevent them any (further) embarassment, (all emphasis mine):</p>

<blockquote><p>[Multi-national company] is rolling out Sharepoint this year. It
<strong>will</strong> provide the organization with an enhanced way of
communicating, collaborating and managing content - a dynamic platform
on which to evolve and further improve [company’s] way or working.
From an internal communications perspective, the Microsoft Office
product provides an <strong>updated way</strong> to engage colleagues, in order to
drive winning culture and business performance. This session captures
the opportunities, benefits, <strong>and realities</strong> of implementing and
living with Sharepoint.</p>

<p>[Employee name], Internal Communications Director, [company].</p></blockquote>

<p>Did I read that correctly? The company haven’t actually implemented the
technology yet, but they are still fronting someone to sell it’s future
virtues.</p>

<p>Whether or not the technology is able to deliver these benefits (and I
<a href="http://twitter.com/jasonwryan/status/839079414">doubt it</a> <a href="http://twitter.com/jasonwryan/status/839079197">very
much</a>), shouldn’t the
corporate communicator at least be talking about, oh let’s say for a
whim, something <em>grounded in evidence?</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
