<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: community | jasonwryan.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/categories/community/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-07-19T19:23:36+12:00</updated>
  <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jason Ryan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Myth of Breakage]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2012/07/19/breakage/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-19T19:23:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2012/07/19/breakage</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="https://dl.dropbox.com/u/261312/Blog-images/broken.jpg" title="Image of breakage on Flickr" >
Breakage is one of the memes of the Arch Linux community; it is referenced frequently on the
<a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/" title="Arch Linux BBS">Arch boards</a> and in the various
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/IRC_Channels" title="Wiki page listing channels">IRC channels</a>.
It doesn't take newcomers long to realize that, whether something is actually broken or not,
there is always
<a href="http://allanmcrae.com/category/arch-linux/" title="Allan's Blog">someone they can blame</a><sup>1</sup>.</p>

<p>My experience of Arch, over the last three and a bit years, is quite the opposite. I have yet to
experience anything that would qualify as breakage. Sure, there have been bugs, mostly upstream,
and the more frequent moments where I haven't been as diligent as I should, but not once have I
had a machine that was unbootable or otherwise unusable. Arch has, on both my home and work
machines, been incredibly stable and reliable.</p>

<p>For a number of Arch Linux users, however, that was not their experience over the last week when
<a href="http://www.archlinux.org/news/the-lib-directory-becomes-a-symlink/" title="News item on the move">/lib was moved to /usr/lib</a>.
The volume of people on the boards and on IRC reporting unbootable or unusable systems was
remarkable. Remarkable because, despite the fact that the
<a href="http://www.archlinux.org/news/the-lib-directory-becomes-a-symlink/" title="Once more, just in case…">news item</a>, the
<a href="http://www.archlinux.org/news/the-lib-directory-becomes-a-symlink/" title="Arch wiki page on the change">wiki page</a>,
and the <a href="http://mailman.archlinux.org/pipermail/arch-announce/2012-July/000317.html" title="Mail archive">email to arch-announce</a>
all <em>explicitly</em> warned people not to use the <code>--force</code> option,<sup>2</sup> so many did.</p>

<p><span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='90% of the breakage was because people either didn&#8217;t see, or disregarded, that advice. '>
Sadly, these red-boxed warnings were apparently not enough.
90% of the breakage was because people either didn't see, or disregarded, that advice.
The remaining 10% were either in a hurry and didn't pay close attention to how
to deal with any leftover files in <span class="file">/lib</span> or <code>rm -rf</code>'ed
in the wrong directory.
<a href="http://www.gnu.org/fun/jokes/shit-happens.html" title="GNU Humour…">Accidents happen</a>.
</span></p>

<p>What I am interested in is the people who fell into the much larger category,
and principally those that didn't see any of the communications about this
change in advance of updating and reasoned, based on a recent change that did
<a href="http://www.archlinux.org/news/filesystem-upgrade-manual-intervention-required-1/" title="News item on filesystem upgrade">require the use of --force</a>,
that this was the most expedient way to resolve <code>pacman</code> reporting conflicting
files.</p>

<p>Some context. The <code>glibc</code> update was released to the
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Testing#.5Btesting.5D" title="Wiki entry on Testing">[testing] repository</a>
in the first week of July: and there were a couple of long threads<sup>3</sup>
about issues and fixes before it was pushed to [core]. By the time the
package was released for general consumption, it had been tested and the
developers had obviously planned how to make what is a fundamental system
change with a minimal amount of user intervention.  I think that, given the
magnitude of the challenge, they did a superb job.</p>

<p>How then did it go so wrong for so many?<sup>4</sup> To answer that, you have
to consider the nature of Arch. It's <em>not</em> the sort of distribution where you
install it and then just go on your merry way, installing
<a href="http://oswatershed.org/" title="It's SCIENCE, Jim">the least obsolete packages</a>,
revelling in the speed of the package manager and generally being
a 1337 h@x0r…</p>

<p>Successfully running a rolling release like Arch, irrespective of your level of
competence, means staying in touch with what is happening—in
<a href="http://kmkeen.com/pacmatic/" title="Pacman wrapper that pulls news updates">some form or other</a>.
Subscribing to the arch-general <acronym title="Mailing list">ML</acronym>,
visiting the forums, idling in IRC; somehow remaining connected to what is
going on in the community so that you don't blindly update one day and wonder
why your system is broken.</p>

<p>This strikes me as a real strength; by design Arch encourages its users to
participate in the community. Even if you are only lurking, over time you will
inevitably find yourself posting in a thread, responding to an email, editing
the wiki,
<a href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2012/03/09/aurphan/" title="Post on aurphan">adopting an orphaned package</a>—increasingly
getting involved and contributing.</p>

<p>This level of involvement is not for everyone. Some may find it onerous or
a waste of their time. That's fine. There are any number of other distros
that do not ask for this level of commitment. The <em>quid pro quo</em> for
running Arch, though, is that you are prepared, in whatever shape or form
best works for you, to give something back; at the very least, that is your
attention.</p>

<h4>Notes</h4>

<ol>
<li><p>This is, of course, a reference to said Arch meme: Allan is one
of the developers who has contributed an enormous amount to Arch and the fact
that his IRC nick is <code>allanbrokeit</code> is purely coincidental.</p></li>
<li><p>At the end of 2011, the short option <code>-f</code>
<a href="http://mailman.archlinux.org/pipermail/pacman-dev/2011-October/014589.html" title="Post to ML anouncing change">was removed</a>
from <code>pacman</code> so “it at least makes people read the word 'force' and maybe they
will have some sense to step back and think about what they are doing first.”</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?id=144620">https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?id=144620</a> and
<a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?id=144616">https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?id=144616</a></p></li>
<li><p>Relatively speaking. In situations like this, the overwhelming amount of traffic
is about what went wrong, not people posting to say they had no difficulties whatsoever…</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Creative Commons image on Flickr from
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/daviddoctorrose/431786001/" title="Broken keyboard on Flickr">djeucalyptus</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Misunderstanding Arch]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2012/06/16/misunderstanding/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-16T10:52:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2012/06/16/misunderstanding</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/261312/Blog-images/hands.jpg" title="'mutt logo'" ></p>

<p>I am frequently struck by how many people arrive on the
<a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/" title="Arch Linux Forums">Arch boards</a> without <em>any</em>
understanding of how Arch is different from the other GNU/Linux communities
they may have spent time with (if, indeed, they have spent any time in
another community before trying Arch). For me, this is akin to arriving in a
foreign country and not bothering to familiarize yourself at all with the local
mores and customs; it lies on a spectrum somewhere between ignorance and
outright arrogance.</p>

<p>The result, inevitably, is that these people are shocked
when their expectations of how they <em>should</em> be treated are at odds with the
reception their behaviour invites…</p>

<p>Before venturing any further, I should preface my remarks about this with
something of a disclaimer. These are my own views and not those of the current,
or past, forum staff.</p>

<p>One of Arch's significant acheivements is the quality of
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org" title="THE best GNU/Linux Wiki">its documentation</a>.
Not just the technical documentation describing how to install and configure
Arch, but the cultural documentation that sets out
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/The_Arch_Way" title="The Arch Way">Arch's philosophy</a>
and <a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Forum_Etiquette" title="Forum Etiquette">standards of behaviour</a>. Both these pages provide clear statements on what to expect when
using Arch Linux and a clear indication of how to respectfully interact with the
community when you are seeking help.</p>

<p>The defining statement about Arch's intended user base is quite direct and
unambiguous:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Arch Linux targets and accommodates competent GNU/Linux users<br/>by giving them complete control and responsibility over the system.</p><footer><strong>The Arch Way</strong> <cite><a href='https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/The_Arch_Way#User-centric'>wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/&hellip;</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>The expression “targets and accommodates” doesn't exclude other users—for
example, those that are not necessarily competent, but are wanting to learn
more about the specifics of how their machines work—it does, however, signal
quite explicitly what sort of community Arch is. And what it is not.</p>

<p><a href="http://ubuntu.com" title="Ubuntu Linux">Ubuntu</a> is an excellent distribution. Like Arch,
it has very specific aims and a clear concept of what the Ubuntu community is.
Popularity is central to Ubuntu's culture. People coming from Ubuntu, who
haven't bothered to familiarize themselves with Arch's values, often struggle
to appreciate the difference; leading to comments like this one:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Maybe if Arch is friendly and Arch forum is friendly, it might go some<br/>place, who knows…</p><footer><strong>Linux Journal commenter</strong> <cite><a href='http://www.linuxjournal.com/content/arch-way#comment-361974'>www.linuxjournal.com/content/&hellip;</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>This was posted in reply to a post on Arch in which the author noted how to
seek help with Arch Linux:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>You'll find far less hand-holding on the Arch Forums than some of the other<br/>distro's forums, and for good reason.  Arch has one of the most informative,<br/>user-friendly wiki's out there. Do not, I repeat, DO NOT ask a question in the<br/>forums or on IRC without searching the wiki and the forums first.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Similarly, looking through the threads in
<a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewforum.php?id=23" title="Newbie board">Newbie Corner</a>
will periodically turn up new posters who are indignant at being told to
<acronym title="Read The Fscking Manual">RTFM</acronym> and see it as some
sort of <em>personal</em> attack, when in fact it is just someone pointing out the
obvious to them. The community hasn't compiled all that documentation just
so they can sit around and regurgitate answers for people who are either
unwilling or incapable of making the minimum amount of  effort required to
solve their own problems…</p>

<p>If you want handholding, there are plenty of online communities that will
cater for you. If you install Arch and think that you are automatically entitled
to immediate support for issues that you encounter, then you are mistaken.
If you think that Arch will suffer if you don't get what you want, then
your problems extend significantly beyond your choice of distro.</p>

<p>The community has worked hard over the years to keep the signal-to-noise ratio
on the boards high, that way, the forums remain a helpful resource for the community,
not a breeding ground for
<a href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2012/03/17/vampires/" title="Post on parasites…">help vampires</a>.</p>

<h4>Notes</h4>

<p>Flickr Creative Commons image by
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/angellic/47031159/">si_si_ay</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Taxonomy of Help Vampires]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2012/03/17/vampires/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-17T16:25:00+13:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2012/03/17/vampires</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/261312/Blog-images/vampire1.jpg" alt="image" /></p>

<p>If you have spent any time at all amongst online (or, for that matter,
off-line) communities, you will be familiar with the help vampire. If,
by some combination of fortune and ignorance, you haven’t come across
this term before, read Amy Hoy’s original—and definitive—
<a href="http://slash7.com/2006/12/22/vampires/" title="Amy's blog on help vampires">post on this scourge</a>,
<em>now</em>.</p>

<p>Amy has some excellent tips on identifying help vampires, however, since
she originally shed some sunlight on this odious species, they have
become even more cunning and have adapted; to the point where there are
now several varieties that you should be wary of if you are determined
to prevent your online community from becoming overrun with them.</p>

<p><strong>The Infant</strong> The easiest to spot because, due to their nascent form,
they have not developed sophisticated anti-detection strategies as yet.
Also, encouragingly, these are the most likely to respond to the
corrective measures Amy outlines in her post.</p>

<p>The infant has probably learned their dependant ways in some other
online community with a higher tolerance for their spoonfeeding needs.
Corrective measures, vigorously and repeatedly applied <em>can</em> turn them
around; but even small amounts of reinforcement of this behaviour can
quickly see them morph into one of the more sinister types…</p>

<p><img src="http://media.tumblr.com/tumblr_m10ce18Jda1qz8s9s.jpg" alt="image" /></p>

<p><strong>The Leech</strong> This reprehensible lifeform just sucks and sucks and
<em>sucks</em> until there is nothing left. Some of their forum threads may
even appear reasonable, but looking at their profile in totality tells a
shocking story. All of their posts are in their own threads, they are
not interested in helping anyone else with a problem. They will move
remorselessly from issue to issue, expecting the community to provide
answers for them at a hemorrhagic rate.</p>

<p>They won’t have made any edits to
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org" title="The BEST godamn GNU/Linux wiki on the web">the Wiki</a>,
no matter how trivial. They won’t
<a href="https://aur.archlinux.org" title="Arch User repository">maintain any packages</a> or donate
any time or
<a href="http://www.archlinux.org/donate/" title="Donate now and recieve a FREE package update!">money</a>
to your community. But they will be there night after night, posting
their problems and waiting for the hapless to expend their time and
energy on them. Like all parasites, they will adapt over time so remain
vigilant.</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/261312/Blog-images/vampire3.jpg" alt="image" /></p>

<p><strong>The Fanger</strong> The out-and-out help vampire, unabashed and unashamed of
their <em>needs</em>. Their sense of entitlement will be telegraphed by needy
and demanding thread titles, often featuring exhortations like “HELP”
and “URGENT” and almost always embellished with a liberal—and, at times
of “real crises,” exclusive—use of all caps and exclamation marks.</p>

<p>The Fanger will also occasionally table (sadly, almost inevitably empty)
threats about leaving your community and going off to use some other
software; as if the dependency relationship is somehow reversed and it
is you, the community, that will suffer if they leave.</p>

<p>The other classic trait of the hardcore vampire is that, like their
fictional avatars, they see nothing when a mirror is held up to them.
You can call their behaviour as much as you like, it will have no
effect. Your only solution here is technology:
<a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2011/06/suspension-ban-or-hellban.html" title="Coding Horror on the Hell Ban">the hell ban</a>.</p>

<hr />

<p>The Arch Linux community has grown considerably since it emerged
<a href="http://www.archlinux.org/news/arch-linux-turns-10/" title="w00t!">ten years ago this month</a>. Over
the last couple of years, the forums in particular have seen a lot of
new users signing up to participate. This is unquestionably a good
thing™</p>

<p>However, Arch is clearly labelled as being for
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/The_Arch_Way#User-centric" title="The Arch Way: user-centric">competent users</a>
(and here competent can equally mean accomplished – or prepared to
invest in themselves and the community to become competent) and that
means not enabling these sorts of vampiric behaviours, in whatever form
they manifest.</p>

<h5>Notes</h5>

<p>Photography is all Creative Commons licensed on Flickr by, in order of
appearance:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/randaldroher/2161723492/" title="The Count, by Randall Drohrer on Flickr">Randall Drohrer</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/phatcontroller/2620032517" title="Leech, by phatcontroler on Flickr">phatcontroller</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sandrafalkevik/4465039571" title="Vampire, by Sandra Falkevik on Flickr">Sandra Falkevik</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quora's Quandary]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2011/05/28/quoras-quandary/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-28T10:05:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2011/05/28/quoras-quandary</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/261312/Blog-images/quora1.png" alt="image" /></p>

<p>I joined <a href="http://www.quora.com/" title="Quora: Q&amp;A site">Quora</a> early in the
new year and, while
<a href="http://techcrunch.com/2011/01/23/why-i-don%E2%80%99t-buy-the-quora-hype/" title="TC article on the hype">the hype has in no way abated</a>,
I have found that increasingly over the months that I have been
visiting, there is less and less reason for me to return on any regular
basis. And this puzzles me as I think the concept is, for me, an
attractive one.</p>

<p>In the five-odd months I have been visiting the site, I have managed to
<a href="http://www.quora.com/Jason-Ryan" title="My Quora profile">contribute 58 answers</a>
and over one hundred edits (more on that below); this strikes me as a reasonable
commitment on my part and one that should return some dividend to me –
at least in terms of satisfaction with the site. Alas, no.</p>

<p>And why not? For several reasons. And reasons that have only really
become apparent over the last month as I started to spend time on the
<a href="http://unix.stackexchange.com/" title="Unix and Linux Stack Exchange">Unix &amp; Linux Stack Exchange site</a>.
The contrast between the <em>experience</em> of the two sites, that are in
essence very similar, couldn’t be more striking.</p>

<p>The primary difference between the two is that Unix.SE isn’t a social
site: you don’t follow anyone. Which, when you think about Q&amp;A sites,
makes a lot more sense than Quora’s model. I still don’t understand the
point of following people on Quora. Perhaps I am not following enough
people, or the wrong ones, but I have yet to see <em>any benefit</em> in
following on the site.</p>

<p>One other area of seeming similarity between the sites is the ability to
vote up (or down) questions and answers. On Unix.SE, this is implemented
as a real strength as these votes determine contributor’s reputation,
described thus:</p>

<blockquote><p>Reputation is a rough measurement of how much the community trusts
you. Reputation is never given, it is earned by convincing fellow
users that you know what you’re talking about.</p></blockquote>

<p>This has a twofold effect: it motivates contributors to provide quality
answers (and
<a href="http://unix.stackexchange.com/badges" title="StackExchange badges">rewards</a>
them when they do), and more importantly, gives you a heuristic for how
credible an answer may be. Quora doesn’t have this concept and, for me,
is much the poorer for it.</p>

<p>Reputation has consequences on Unix.SE: the more you accrue, the more
privileges on the site you are granted. Again, this builds the
community’s capability while encouraging individual contributors.</p>

<p>Some of the other areas where Quora is really left wanting in comparison
to Unix.SE are around the design of the site. The text box where you
enter your answers or edits is a case in point:</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/261312/Blog-images/quora2.png" alt="image" /></p>

<p>On Quora, it is like trying to change a car battery through a letterbox.
The single, overriding impression is that entering information into the
site is neither a priority nor pleasurable which, for a site aspiring to
be a knowledge repository is incredibly perverse.</p>

<p>This is compounded by the fact that the tools for presenting the
information that you want to add to the site can charitably be described
as rudimentary (one of the reasons that I have 100-odd edits is that it
takes at least two to three attempts to present information in a
semi-acceptable fashion). Searching for
“<a href="http://www.quora.com/Quora-product/Are-there-any-markup-tags-when-writing-a-question?q=quora+markup+tools" title="Recursion alert">quora markup tools</a>”
is as disappointing as it is frustrating.</p>

<p>Being able to present information appropriately is critical. The
StackExchange sites
<a href="http://unix.stackexchange.com/editing-help" title="Unix.SE editing guidleines">allow all sorts</a>
of HTML tags and
<a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/syntax" title="markdown syntax">markdown</a>,
without apparently any additional
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cross-site_scripting" title="Wikipedia page on Cross site scripting">XSS risk</a><sup>1</sup>.
The result is questions and answers that are formatted in a way that
enhances their legibility, rather than detracting from it.</p>

<p>There are some other areas where Quora is not measuring up for me:
opaque editorial and moderation policies and practices and an
unwillingness to more actively curate the questions – and no, those two
statements are not contradictory.</p>

<p>The overall impression I am left with is that while both sites have
similar aims (albeit Unix.SE’s is much more specific in terms of the
subject matter), Quora seems to me to be really failing at building a
community around it. Unless, of course, you count social media experts…</p>

<h5>Notes</h5>

<ol>
<li>God knows if that is actually the reason they refuse to allow
potential contributors the ability to adequately format their
information, but it seems plausible enough.</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
