<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: community | jasonwryan.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/categories/community/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jasonwryan.com/"/>
  <updated>2021-06-24T12:21:36+12:00</updated>
  <id>http://jasonwryan.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jason Ryan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Install scripts]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2014/07/11/aif/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-11T09:49:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2014/07/11/aif</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/post_images/spoons.jpg" title="Creative Commons image of spoons" >
It is now almost exactly two years since the <acronym title="Arch Installer Framework">AIF</acronym>
was <a href="https://www.archlinux.org/news/install-media-20120715-released/" title="Arch News item">put out to pasture</a>.
At the time, it caused a degree of consternation, inexplicably causing some to
believe that it presaged the demise of—if not Arch itself, then certainly the
community around it. And I think it would be fair to say that it was the signal
event that launched a number of spin-offs, the first of which from memory was
Archbang; soon followed by a number of others that promised “Arch Linux with an
easy installation,” or something to that effect…</p>

<p>Of course, if you look back at the Installation Guide immediately before the
move to the new scripts, for example the version that shipped with the last AIF
in
<a href="https://projects.archlinux.org/aif.git/tree/doc/official_installation_guide_en?id=4b075d9cd09b5a0912528bd94ae2a0d4eeb2d7f9" title="In the Git repository">October, 2011</a>, it is pretty evident that
the <a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Installation_guide" title="Installation Guide">current approach</a>
is <em>a lot</em> simpler. Sure, there is no curses <acronym title="Graphic User
Interface">GUI</acronym> to step you through each part of the install but the
introduction of <code>pacstrap</code> and <code>arch-chroot</code> meant that you no longer need those
prompts.</p>

<p>There is also the added advantage that these scripts are useful outside the
installation process itself; they can be used for system maintenance and, in
the rare event that your recent bout of experimentation at 2am after a few
drinks doesn&rsquo;t pan out the way you anticipated, repair.</p>

<p>One of the other responses to the new approach, however, has been the steady
proliferation of “helpful” install scripts. These are essentially bash scripts
that emulate the behaviour of the AIF and walk people through an automated
install of their system. Well, not really their system, more accurately <em>a</em>
system. So you run one of these scripts, answer a few prompts and then, when
you reboot, you have a brand spanking new Arch Linux install running KDE with
the full panoply of software and, in a few special cases, some customized dot
files to “enhance” your experience.</p>

<p>From a certain perspective, I can see how these things appeal. “I wonder if I
could script an entire install, from the partitioning right through to the
desktop environment?” That sounds like a fun project, right? Where it all comes
unstuck, unfortunately, is when the corollary thought appears that suggests
sharing it with the wider community would be a good idea. It is at this point
that a rigorous bout of self-examination about the outcomes that you are
seeking and your base motivations for this act of selflessness are called for.</p>

<p>Whatever those motivations are, whether driven by altruism or the naked desire
for fame and fortune that have—from time to time—alighted on these projects
when they appear on /r/archlinux and the adoring throngs bestow their favours
in equal measures of upvotes and bitcoin, they are grotesquely misplaced. No
good comes from these things, I tell you; none.</p>

<p>Why not? Because, in the guise of being helpful, you are effectively depriving
people of the single most important part of using Arch: building it themselves.
It&rsquo;s like inviting someone to a restaurant for an amazing <em>haute cuisine</em> meal,
sitting them down across the table from you and then them watching as the
staff bring out a mouth-watering array of dishes, each of which you
ostentatiously savour before vomiting it all back into their mouth.</p>

<p>Now, I am sure there is a small minority (well, at least from my own
sheltered experience I imagine it is small) who would
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emetophilia" title="Wikipedia: SFW">relish this scenario</a>,
but for most it would qualify as a pretty disappointing date.</p>

<p>Then, after the technicolour <em>table d'hôte</em>, there is the matter of the
clean up. Recently, we had someone show up on the
<a href="http://bbs.archlinux.org" title="Community forums">Arch boards</a> who had
“installed Arch” but who did not understand how to edit a text file;
literally had no clue how to open a file like <span class="file">/etc/fstab</span>
make some changes and then save it. This is beyond stupid; it is a drain
on the goodwill of the community that has to deal with this ineptitude, it
is unfair on people to put them in a position where they feel they are
at the mercy of their technology, rather than in control of it, and it
does nothing to advance the interests of Arch.</p>

<p>If you want to write something like this to improve your scripting skills,
by all means proceed. If you want to contribute to Arch, then pick a
project to contribute to, some bugs to squash, wiki edits, whatever; just
don&rsquo;t publish another one of these idiotic scripts, because you aren&rsquo;t
doing anyone any favours, quite the contrary.</p>

<h4>Notes</h4>

<p>Flickr Creative Commons image, <a href="https://flic.kr/p/dSK6yG">Measuring spoons</a> by
Theen Moy.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Minimum Standards]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2014/05/03/standards/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-03T10:58:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2014/05/03/standards</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/post_images/crowd.jpg" title="Creative Commons crowd image" >
Late last month there was a post on
<a href="http://meta.stackoverflow.com/questions/251758/why-is-stack-overflow-so-negative-of-late" title="All the hate…">Meta Stack Overflow</a> wondering why SO is “so negative of late.” Reading through the
extensive list of answers, and all the comments that quickly adhered to them
like barnacles on a becalmed schooner, it was hard not to extrapolate to the
experiences of online communities elsewhere, especially in the free and open
software world. Stack Overflow is going on six years old now and has grown to
be a truly formidable<sup>1</sup> resource for programmers, <em>dilettantes</em>—the
category to which I clearly belong—and, apparently, people wanting their
homework done for them. This isn&rsquo;t the first time this question has been raised
there, and I am sure it won&rsquo;t be the last.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t spend <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/users/712613/jasonwryan" title="My SO profile">much time on SO</a>,
mostly because I am not a programmer and so I don&rsquo;t have much to contribute there, but also because
I <a href="http://unix.stackexchange.com/users/6761/jasonwryan" title="U&amp;L profile">am active on Unix &amp; Linux</a><sup>2</sup>,
one of the clones that has emerged out of the metastasizing StackExchange
empire. I do, however, subscribe to quite a few of the <acronym title="Really Simple Syndication">RSS</acronym>
feeds for question tags on SO: things like #awk, #bash, and other topics that are of interest
to me. Given the amount of noise in these feeds; in the form of redundancy (ie., questions
that have been asked in one form or another <em>many</em> times before) or just a signal failure to read
<em>any</em> documentation, it is not surprising that the people responsible for this degradation
see the site as negative, or unfriendly, or elitist. This is perfectly natural: it is the
community attempting to defend itself from
<a href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2012/03/17/vampires/" title="Post on the scourge">help vampires</a>.</p>

<p>What was also quite predictable, given StackExchange&rsquo;s response to this “problem” which was the
2012 <a href="http://blog.stackoverflow.com/2012/07/kicking-off-the-summer-of-love/" title="SE Blog post">Summer of Love</a>
campaign where they wanted to make SO a more friendly place, was that this would only
exacerbate the issue. My experience of the site over that time is that the signal to noise has
not improved at all, quite the contrary. I think that setting an expectation that the site
would be more welcoming has two perverse consequences: first, it validates the perceptions
of the newcomers about purported hostility, and in doing so signals to the existing community
that built the value of the site that their culture needs remediation. Secondly, it signals
more tolerance for behaviours that add no value to the community; so it is hardly surprising
to see those behaviours proliferate.</p>

<p>From time to time the Arch community faces exactly the same criticisms: we are unfriendly,
or elitist. I neither agree with these types of comments, nor am I particularly perturbed by
them. Arch is a small community of volunteers, in order to create an environment where people
who are willing and able to actively contribute, I think is important to ensure that there
are clearly articulated standards<sup>3</sup> and that they are maintained by the
community at large.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t see any scope for increasing the community&rsquo;s tolerance for vampirism or the sort
of self-entitlement that has a sad habit of appearing from time-to-time:</p>

<blockquote> As for the Arch team and their lacking resources, let's take your point at face value.  Now, we've known what the problem is for almost four hours and no fix has been issued.</blockquote>


<p>There is some sort of “problem” that “we” have known about for <em>four hours</em> and
yet, inconceivably<sup>4</sup>, <em>nothing</em> has been done about it?</p>

<p>There is no bug report on the <a href="https://bugs.archlinux.org/" title="Flyspray">Arch tracker</a> so
I am not sure why the collective pronoun is warranted here, that quibble aside; in what
universe is this sort of petulance considered acceptable? The only reasonable response
to this sort of whining is to close the thread and ban the infractor and their progeny, who
will no doubt suffer from the same sort of genetic deficiencies, <em>in perpetuam</em>…</p>

<p>Clearly articulating, and enforcing, minimum standards of behaviour doesn&rsquo;t
make your community hostile or unfriendly; it establishes boundaries for people
that supports respectful collaboration and the effective ability of that
community to self-moderate.  People new to the community who take the time to
read the guidelines and observe how things work will have no problem
adapting<sup>5</sup>. It may not make you popular, but it will make a
significant contribution to the sustainability of the community and the levels
of engagement of those that do contribute and wish to continue doing so.</p>

<h4>Notes</h4>

<ol>
<li>“Fear” and it&rsquo;s synonyms appear with remarkable frequency in that thread and the accompanying one on
<a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=7650799">Hacker News</a>.</li>
<li>I have written about U&amp;L <a href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2011/05/28/quoras-quandary/">previously</a>.</li>
<li>The <a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Forum_Etiquette">Forum Etiquette</a>, for example.</li>
<li>With apologies to Wallace Shawn…</li>
<li>I have written about this <a href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/categories/community/">in the past</a>.</li>
</ol>


<p>Creative Commons photo on Flickr by <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/moonstoneportrait/75687093/">Chris Lester</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Asking for Help]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2013/06/15/asking/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-15T10:39:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2013/06/15/asking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/post_images/bowl.jpg" title="&lsquo;Flickr image of Begging Bowl&rsquo;" >
Another great peristaltic movement in Arch&rsquo;s rolling release digestive system
happened over the last couple of weeks, the move of all binaries
<a href="https://www.archlinux.org/news/binaries-move-to-usrbin-requiring-update-intervention/" title="Arch News update">to /usr/bin</a>.
This move had been foreshadowed for several months and, despite announcements
on the front page of the Arch website, the mailing lists and the release going
through [testing] and the resulting thread on the forums, there was still a
surprising amount of carnage<sup>1</sup> in it&rsquo;s wake.</p>

<p>In the aftermath (although I expect that it will take some months for it to
completely pass through the system), what struck me was not so much the variety
and ingenuity of the ways people had managed to break their installs<sup>2</sup>
as how they approached the community seeking help afterwards.</p>

<p>There are already some fine guides on how to do this, notably
ESR&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.catb.org/esr/faqs/smart-questions.html" title="Just read it…">How to ask Questions the Smart Way</a>
and—specifically for Arch—zendeavour&rsquo;s
<a href="http://redd.it/tjjwr" title="On Reddit">troubleshooting for newcomers</a>;
this isn&rsquo;t an attempt to add or expand on that genre. Rather, it is
a look at a subset of attitudes that some people adopt<sup>3</sup>
as they seek the assistance of the community.</p>

<p>The first is the <strong>blamer</strong>. The proponent of the  “all-guns-blazing” approach.
I&rsquo;ll paraphrase, but there are enough examples on the boards to illustrate the
point: “my system can&rsquo;t boot, it&rsquo;s not my fault and I am here to let you know
that I am unhappy and demand recourse.” This is, unquestionably, the most
puzzling of all the strategies. It is often coupled with the (sadly almost
always empty) threat to abandon the distro and it&rsquo;s apparently beleaguered
community.</p>

<p>Puzzling because I have yet to encounter a single situation in life, online
or off, where opening with hostility and blame is an intelligent approach to
seeking assistance. If you are going to adopt this approach, please supersize
to “rage quit” and expend your energy actually delivering on your threat.</p>

<p>The next is the <strong>wheedler</strong>. Less objectionable than the incendiary approach,
it is nonetheless similarly ineffective. Wheedlers are distinguished by
peppering their posts liberally with declarations of their ineptitude and
“noobness”, in the mistaken belief that this will engender a wave of sympathy
prior to soothing hand-holding and spoon-feeding. There is a strong correlation
between this behaviour and the various types of
<a href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2012/03/17/vampires/" title="Post on the taxonomy of vampires">help vampirism</a>.</p>

<p>Wheedling won&rsquo;t lead to quicker, or more informed, advice and assistance; in
all likelihood it will just discourage others from helping because
they can see that rewarding this sort of behaviour has a longer-term
deleterious impact on the health of the community.</p>

<p>Then there is the <strong>Vulcan</strong>. A curiosity more than an annoyance, these
people seem to inhabit some sort of adolescent fantasy land where the Internet
is a venue for them to revel in their almost superhero-like powers of technical
<em>awesomeness</em>; said powers manifesting to others as a sort of benign
cluelessness.</p>

<p>Their posts are invariably brief and completely devoid of relevant detail to the
point of cryptic because, “hey, we all <em>know</em> what this issue is,” and are
littered with smilies and that stupid emoticon with the sunglasses. Rather than
actually describing their problem, they want people to think that, by a process
of <a href="http://en.memory-alpha.org/wiki/Vulcan_mind_meld" title="There is a Star Trek wiki?">mind-melding</a>,
other “hackers” will intuit the subtle depth and intricacy of the issue and
then type out a detailed step-by-step guide of how to solve it.</p>

<p>Finally, there is the <strong>conspiracist</strong>. These malcontents see every
significant change in Arch as being part of a wider agenda to corrupt the purity
of the UNIX® philosophy. They also tend to blame
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lennart_Poettering" title="Lennarts wikipedia page">Lennart Poettering</a>
for <em>everything</em>. These unfortunates are clearly already suffering such mental anguish
trying to reconcile their obsessiveness about the past with a rolling
release that they deserve our pity more than our contempt (but I am equally
happy providing either)…</p>

<p>As I said, these are fortunately just a subset and very much represent the
minority of attitudes.  The vast majority tend to be aware that, at
one time or another, <em>everyone</em> will need some help to solve a problem.
Therefore it is best to approach it in a matter-of-fact way, using the practical
guidance on asking questions on a technical forum, and with a degree of humility
and a willingness to learn from the people who are prepared to share their
knowledge and experience.</p>

<h4>Notes</h4>

<ol>
<li>Where “carnage” should be understood as a minor PEBKAC epidemia…</li>
<li>From shutting down mid-update (because a reboot fixes <em>everything</em>) to
still using <code>consolekit</code>, <code>initscripts</code> and <code>grub-legacy</code>: all deprecated some time
ago.</li>
<li>I resisted linking to specific posts on the boards to provide actual examples,
the more motivated among you will find them without difficulty.</li>
</ol>


<p>Flickr Creative Commons image by
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/buddhist_fox/4795942625/">Buddhist Fox</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[AUR Helpers]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2013/04/09/helpers/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-09T19:07:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2013/04/09/helpers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/post_images/crutches.jpg" title="&lsquo;Crutches on Flickr&rsquo;" ></p>

<h3>Or, &ldquo;Why you should uninstall Yaourt and embrace <em>makepkg</em>…&rdquo;</h3>

<p>The <a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?id=160655" title="Announcement on the Arch boards">release of Pacman 4.1</a>
saw the same flurry of posts on the boards, in IRC and the mailing lists about
people being “unable” to upgrade or, worse, claiming that pacman was “broken”
because their upgrade was failing due to unsatisfied dependencies, that pretty
much every pacman upgrade ocassions. How is it possible that so many people can
run an operating system designed for competent users without having even a
basic understanding of how the package manager—one of the single most critical
components of the distribution—works?</p>

<p>Even a cursory perusal of the resulting threads on the boards will quickly
identify the common denominator in these cases:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>resolving dependencies&hellip;<br/>looking for inter-conflicts&hellip;<br/>error: failed to prepare transaction (could not satisfy dependencies)<br/>:: package-query: requires pacman&lt;4.1</p></blockquote></p>

<p><a href="https://aur.archlinux.org/packages/package-query/" title="AUR page">package-query</a>
is required by <a href="https://aur.archlinux.org/packages/yaourt/" title="yaourt on AUR">yaourt</a>;
so these upgrades have been stymied by a package that is in the (unsupported)
<acronym title="Arch User Repository">AUR</acronym>? There are a
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/AUR_Helpers" title="Arch Wiki entry">multitude of AUR helpers</a>,
but <code>yaourt</code> is most commonly used by people who are new to Arch<sup>1</sup>
for two reasons.  First, it is one of the most “featureful” and secondly, and
more to the point of my argument, it can be installed by simply adding an
unsupported repo to <code>pacman.conf</code>; thereby effectively bypassing the need for
the hapless user ever having to use or understand <code>makepkg</code>.</p>

<p>Consequently, over time, people who are habitually using <code>yaourt -Syu --aur</code> to
update both the packages in the supported repositories and those they have
installed from the AUR lose the conceptual distinction between the two.
<code>yaourt</code> obscures this from them and—if they are completely reliant upon it, as
these threads attest they are—they have abnegated responsibility for managing
those unsupported packages and in doing so have found themselves incapable of
understanding the bind they are in.</p>

<p>This sort of obscuring of fundamental operating principles in the pursuit of
“convenience” is anathema to Arch and is precisely the reason I moved away from
using <code>yaourt</code> (and indeed from using Ubuntu when I jumped from that sinking
ship). Any convenience is purely illusory, in reality it just fosters
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Learned_helplessness" title="Wikipedia entry">learned helplessness</a>.</p>

<p>I understand that the <code>yaourt</code> developer(s) was scratching their own itch, and
this post is not about maligning the project; but there are significant
unintended consequences of giving people a tool that abstracts such a
fundamental element of the distribution away from the user, especially for a
distribution where you are expected to have
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/The_Arch_Way#User-centric" title="The Arch Way">complete control <em>and responsbility</em> over your system</a>.</p>

<p>To be clear, I don&rsquo;t have a complaint with the <em>concept</em> of AUR helpers. I used
<code>yaourt</code> initially before switching to
<a href="http://pbrisbin.com/posts/aurget" title="Patrick Brisbin's AUR helper">aurget</a> and then
alighting on
<a href="https://github.com/falconindy/cower" title="Cower on github">cower</a>, or more particularly,
a partial wrapper for <code>cower</code>:</p>

<p><figure class='code'><figcaption><span>cowerd </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='sh'><span class='line'>&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;h1&gt;!/bin/sh&lt;/h1&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;h1&gt;install AUR packages with cower&lt;/h1&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;cd <span class="nv">$HOME</span>/Build <span class="p">&amp;</span>amp<span class="p">;&amp;</span>amp<span class="p">;</span> cower -d <span class="p">&amp;</span>ldquo<span class="p">;</span><span class="nv">$1</span><span class="p">&amp;</span>rdquo<span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">builddir</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="p">&amp;</span>ldquo<span class="p">;</span><span class="nv">$_</span><span class="p">&amp;</span>rdquo<span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nb">cd</span> <span class="p">&amp;</span>ldquo<span class="p">;</span><span class="nv">$builddir</span><span class="p">&amp;</span>rdquo<span class="p">;</span> <span class="p">&amp;</span>amp<span class="p">;&amp;</span>amp<span class="p">;</span> <span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">EDITOR</span><span class="k">:-</span><span class="nv">vi</span><span class="k">}</span> PKGBUILD <span class="o">||</span> <span class="nb">exit</span>&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;makepkg -si <span class="p">&amp;</span>amp<span class="p">;&amp;</span>amp<span class="p">;</span> <span class="nb">cd</span> - <span class="p">&amp;</span>amp<span class="p">;</span>&gt;/dev/null&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;read -p <span class="p">&amp;</span>ldquo<span class="p">;</span>Remove Build directory? <span class="o">[</span>Y/n<span class="o">]</span>? <span class="p">&amp;</span>rdquo<span class="p">;</span> yn
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">if</span> <span class="o">[</span> <span class="p">&amp;</span>ldquo<span class="p">;</span><span class="nv">$yn</span><span class="p">&amp;</span>rdquo<span class="p">;</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">&amp;</span>ldquo<span class="p">;</span>y<span class="p">&amp;</span>rdquo<span class="p">;</span> <span class="o">]</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="k">then</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nb">printf</span> <span class="p">&amp;</span>ldquo<span class="p">;</span><span class="se">\n</span>%s<span class="se">\n</span><span class="p">&amp;</span>rdquo<span class="p">;</span> <span class="p">&amp;</span>ldquo<span class="p">;</span>Removing build directory<span class="p">&amp;</span>hellip<span class="p">;&amp;</span>rdquo<span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    rm -rf <span class="p">&amp;</span>ldquo<span class="p">;</span><span class="nv">$builddir</span><span class="p">&amp;</span>rdquo<span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">else</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nb">printf</span> <span class="p">&amp;</span>ldquo<span class="p">;</span>%s<span class="se">\n</span><span class="p">&amp;</span>rdquo<span class="p">;</span> <span class="p">&amp;</span>ldquo<span class="p">;</span>Build completed.<span class="p">&amp;</span>rdquo<span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">fi</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></p>

<p>This provides me the minimum level of automation I require—essentially only
around downloading and installing a package. It doesn&rsquo;t automatically handle
dependencies, nor manage updating the packages; that remains, rightly in my
view, <em>my</em> responsibility.</p>

<p>If I were to look to a more fully featured wrapper, I would undoubtedly choose
<a href="https://github.com/e36freak/meat" title="meat on Github">meat</a>, however as on my
desktop machine, I only have ~30 AUR packages installed, I don&rsquo;t really need
anything more sophisticated.</p>

<p>So by all means, use an AUR helper. But recognize that it is intended to help
you, not preclude you from being able to accomplish the most simple and
critical task of system maintenance, updating your package manager. Uninstall
<code>yaourt</code> if you are using it and familiarize yourself with <code>makepkg</code>; once you
do understand the relationship between the official repositories and the AUR,
download <code>cower</code> or <code>meat</code>, they are both <em>much</em> better solutions.</p>

<h4>Notes</h4>

<ol>
<li><a href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2009/11/21/dzen2-and-conky-cli-in-dwm/" title="Post from 2009">Myself included</a>…</li>
</ol>


<p>Creative Commons image of crutches by
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/wheatfields/118700600/" title="Flickr CC image">net_efekt on Flickr</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Forking Arch]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2013/03/02/forking/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-02T10:04:00+13:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2013/03/02/forking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/post_images/fork.jpg" title="&lsquo;Fork on Flickr&rsquo;" >
Over the last couple of months there have been a number of discussions on the Arch boards
about the
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Forum_Etiquette#Arch_Linux_Distribution_Support_ONLY" title="Forum Etiquette">forum policy</a>
of only providing support for Arch Linux, culminating in this
<a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?id=157361" title="Arch Forum thread">long thread about Archbang users</a>
(login required) being denied support and having their threads summarily
closed. As it emerged in the discussion, there seem to be two separate issues
at play here; the question of Arch-derivatives using the Arch brand (logo,
colours and even the forum style sheets), and how the wider community of
GNU/Linux distributions are treated on our boards.</p>

<p>The first issue is relatively simple to address. Allowing derivative
distributions to use the Arch brand is, in my view, a mistake. It dilutes the
value of the Arch “brand” and—as can be seen when people show up having
installed a derivative and thinking they are running Arch—just confuses people.</p>

<p>For some of these derivatives, like Archbang, there is an argument to be made
that once they have completed the installation process, they are in fact
running Arch, albeit an off-the-shelf version. I find this argument to be
specious. All of the derivatives that I have come across, in addition to
“simplifying”<sup>1</sup> the installation process and including <code>X</code> and some
sort of desktop or window manager by default, also make a number of other
system changes that invalidate their claim to being Arch by another name.</p>

<p>See this <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/archlinux/comments/yj2v5/a_new_guibased_version_of_arch_has_gone_live/c5wc6yo" title="Reddit thread on Manjaro Linux">scathing review of Manjaro</a>
or Allan&rsquo;s <a href="http://allanmcrae.com/2012/12/battle-of-the-arch-spin-offs/" title="Allan McRae's blog">roundup of the Arch Spin-Offs</a>
for the details on the decisions these developers make that mean it is not
practicable to support them on the Arch boards, nor desirable to do so in
future. As a distro, Arch is essentially vanilla packages, pacman and rolling
release, and a base on which
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/The_Arch_Way#User-centric" title="The Arch Way">you build your preferred system</a>.
Changing two of those three means that you are not running Arch…</p>

<p>That leads in to the second point, which is I&rsquo;ll paraphrase as “well, we are
all Linux users, so everyone should be welcome to ask for support from Arch
users.” It is a fine sentiment, but one that is neither
<a href="http://www.catb.org/esr/faqs/smart-questions.html#forum" title="ESR's seminal document">historically accurate</a>,
nor in the long term interests of Arch. I have harped on in the past about
<a href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2012/03/17/vampires/" title="My post on the taxonomy of suckers…">help vampires</a>
and last year I came across the perfect illustration of the unchecked effects
of this phenomena:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Right now I&rsquo;d say the bug queues are flooded with bugs that you can&rsquo;t really act on… It&rsquo;s a strain on the project that there are so many users that don&rsquo;t really get it.</p><footer><strong>Alison Randall</strong> <cite>Ubuntu Technical Architect. Linux Format July 2012</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Your bugtracker becomes essentially unusable. Your forums end up the same way.
No-one ends up getting much in the way of assistance at all, let alone anything
approaching informed help. That may be an inevitable consequence of the
collision between considerable but still finite resources and a philosophy of being
the <acronym title="Operating System">OS</acronym> of the masses; Arch has
nothing like that in terms of resources, and a very different
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/The_Arch_Way" title="The Arch Way, again…">philosophy</a>.</p>

<p>That philosophy doesn&rsquo;t include anything about shortcuts or commoditized images
for a mass user base. It doesn&rsquo;t mention making the installation and
maintenance of your system completely idiot-proof so as to facilitate a
relentless march to the very top of whatever spurious distro popularity ranking
system you subscribe to. And it certainly doesn&rsquo;t say anything about your
entitlement to immediate and courteous support from the Arch community in the
face of your own inability to reach a minimum level of understanding of what it
is that you have installed on your hard drive.</p>

<p>If you think that you can just skip the whole tiresome
<a href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2013/02/08/documentation/" title="Post on documentation">RTFM thing</a>
by downloading a derivative and installing that, how exactly do you expect to be able
to run a rolling release distro that has, on average, a couple of
<a href="https://www.archlinux.org/news/" title="Arch news">significant changes</a> every year?</p>

<p>Sooner or later you are going to have to come to terms with <em>the responsibility</em>
that is an integral part of this type of rolling release and, if you have
installed it yourself, you will be much better placed to be able to build on
that understanding and broaden and deepen your knowledge of your system.</p>

<p>That is ultimately far more satisfying for you, and much more beneficial for
the rest of the community as it means that you will be more able and likely to
contribute back in whatever way that you can; reporting bugs to a functioning
bug tracker, editing the <a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org" title="The finest, actually">fine Wiki</a>,
maintaining packages in <a href="https://aur.archlinux.org" title="Arch User Repository">the AUR</a>,
submitting patches, etc.  Doing all the things that will
sustain Arch and continue to make it an attractive distribution for competent
GNU/Linux users and those that are willing to invest the time to become so.</p>

<h4>Notes</h4>

<ol>
<li>If you have used the Arch install scripts, you would appreciate that it is
not really possible to provide a simpler installation process.</li>
</ol>


<p>Creative Commons licensed image on Flickr by <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/pietroizzo/3514191996/">pietroizzo</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
