<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: community | jasonwryan.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/categories/community/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-26T13:59:38+12:00</updated>
  <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jason Ryan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Asking for Help]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2013/06/15/asking/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-15T10:39:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2013/06/15/asking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/261312/Blog-images/bowl.jpg" title="'Flickr image of Begging Bowl'" >
Another great peristaltic movement in Arch's rolling release digestive system
happened over the last couple of weeks, the move of all binaries
<a href="https://www.archlinux.org/news/binaries-move-to-usrbin-requiring-update-intervention/" title="Arch News update">to /usr/bin</a>.
This move had been foreshadowed for several months and, despite announcements
on the front page of the Arch website, the mailing lists and the release going
through [testing] and the resulting thread on the forums, there was still a
surprising amount of carnage<sup>1</sup> in it's wake.</p>

<p>In the aftermath (although I expect that it will take some months for it to
completely pass through the system), what struck me was not so much the variety
and ingenuity of the ways people had managed to break their installs<sup>2</sup>
as how they approached the community seeking help afterwards.</p>

<p>There are already some fine guides on how to do this, notably
ESR's <a href="http://www.catb.org/esr/faqs/smart-questions.html" title="Just read it…">How to ask Questions the Smart Way</a>
and—specifically for Arch—zendeavour's
<a href="http://redd.it/tjjwr" title="On Reddit">troubleshooting for newcomers</a>;
this isn't an attempt to add or expand on that genre. Rather, it is
a look at a subset of attitudes that some people adopt<sup>3</sup>
as they seek the assistance of the community.</p>

<p>The first is the <strong>blamer</strong>. The proponent of the  “all-guns-blazing” approach.
I'll paraphrase, but there are enough examples on the boards to illustrate the
point: “my system can't boot, it's not my fault and I am here to let you know
that I am unhappy and demand recourse.” This is, unquestionably, the most
puzzling of all the strategies. It is often coupled with the (sadly almost
always empty) threat to abandon the distro and it's apparently beleaguered
community.</p>

<p>Puzzling because I have yet to encounter a single situation in life, online
or off, where opening with hostility and blame is an intelligent approach to
seeking assistance. If you are going to adopt this approach, please supersize
to “rage quit” and expend your energy actually delivering on your threat.</p>

<p>The next is the <strong>wheedler</strong>. Less objectionable than the incendiary approach,
it is nonetheless similarly ineffective. Wheedlers are distinguished by
peppering their posts liberally with declarations of their ineptitude and
“noobness”, in the mistaken belief that this will engender a wave of sympathy
prior to soothing hand-holding and spoon-feeding. There is a strong correlation
between this behaviour and the various types of
<a href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2012/03/17/vampires/" title="Post on the taxonomy of vampires">help vampirism</a>.</p>

<p>Wheedling won't lead to quicker, or more informed, advice and assistance; in
all likelihood it will just discourage others from helping because
they can see that rewarding this sort of behaviour has a longer-term
deleterious impact on the health of the community.</p>

<p>Then there is the <strong>Vulcan</strong>. A curiosity more than an annoyance, these
people seem to inhabit some sort of adolescent fantasy land where the Internet
is a venue for them to revel in their almost superhero-like powers of technical
<em>awesomeness</em>; said powers manifesting to others as a sort of benign
cluelessness.</p>

<p>Their posts are invariably brief and completely devoid of relevant detail to the
point of cryptic because, “hey, we all <em>know</em> what this issue is,” and are
littered with smilies and that stupid emoticon with the sunglasses. Rather than
actually describing their problem, they want people to think that, by a process
of <a href="http://en.memory-alpha.org/wiki/Vulcan_mind_meld" title="There is a Star Trek wiki?">mind-melding</a>,
other “hackers” will intuit the subtle depth and intricacy of the issue and
then type out a detailed step-by-step guide of how to solve it.</p>

<p>Finally, there is the <strong>conspiracist</strong>. These malcontents see every
significant change in Arch as being part of a wider agenda to corrupt the purity
of the UNIX® philosophy. They also tend to blame
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lennart_Poettering" title="Lennarts wikipedia page">Lennart Poettering</a>
for <em>everything</em>. These unfortunates are clearly already suffering such mental anguish
trying to reconcile their obsessiveness about the past with a rolling
release that they deserve our pity more than our contempt (but I am equally
happy providing either)…</p>

<p>As I said, these are fortunately just a subset and very much represent the
minority of attitudes.  The vast majority tend to be aware that, at
one time or another, <em>everyone</em> will need some help to solve a problem.
Therefore it is best to approach it in a matter-of-fact way, using the practical
guidance on asking questions on a technical forum, and with a degree of humility
and a willingness to learn from the people who are prepared to share their
knowledge and experience.</p>

<h4>Notes</h4>

<ol>
<li>Where “carnage” should be understood as a minor PEBKAC epidemia…</li>
<li>From shutting down mid-update (because a reboot fixes <em>everything</em>) to
still using <code>consolekit</code>, <code>initscripts</code> and <code>grub-legacy</code>: all deprecated some time
ago.</li>
<li>I resisted linking to specific posts on the boards to provide actual examples,
the more motivated among you will find them without difficulty.</li>
</ol>


<p>Flickr Creative Commons image by
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/buddhist_fox/4795942625/">Buddhist Fox</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[AUR Helpers]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2013/04/09/helpers/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-09T19:07:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2013/04/09/helpers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/261312/Blog-images/crutches.jpg" title="'Crutches on Flickr'" ></p>

<h3>Or, "Why you should uninstall Yaourt and embrace <em>makepkg</em>…"</h3>

<p>The <a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?id=160655" title="Announcement on the Arch boards">release of Pacman 4.1</a>
saw the same flurry of posts on the boards, in IRC and the mailing lists about
people being “unable” to upgrade or, worse, claiming that pacman was “broken”
because their upgrade was failing due to unsatisfied dependencies, that pretty
much every pacman upgrade ocassions. How is it possible that so many people can
run an operating system designed for competent users without having even a
basic understanding of how the package manager—one of the single most critical
components of the distribution—works?</p>

<p>Even a cursory perusal of the resulting threads on the boards will quickly
identify the common denominator in these cases:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>resolving dependencies...<br/>looking for inter-conflicts...<br/>error: failed to prepare transaction (could not satisfy dependencies)<br/>:: package-query: requires pacman&lt;4.1</p></blockquote></p>

<p><a href="https://aur.archlinux.org/packages/package-query/" title="AUR page">package-query</a>
is required by <a href="https://aur.archlinux.org/packages/yaourt/" title="yaourt on AUR">yaourt</a>;
so these upgrades have been stymied by a package that is in the (unsupported)
<acronym title="Arch User Repository">AUR</acronym>? There are a
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/AUR_Helpers" title="Arch Wiki entry">multitude of AUR helpers</a>,
but <code>yaourt</code> is most commonly used by people who are new to Arch<sup>1</sup>
for two reasons.  First, it is one of the most “featureful” and secondly, and
more to the point of my argument, it can be installed by simply adding an
unsupported repo to <code>pacman.conf</code>; thereby effectively bypassing the need for
the hapless user ever having to use or understand <code>makepkg</code>.</p>

<p>Consequently, over time, people who are habitually using <code>yaourt -Syu --aur</code> to
update both the packages in the supported repositories and those they have
installed from the AUR lose the conceptual distinction between the two.
<code>yaourt</code> obscures this from them and—if they are completely reliant upon it, as
these threads attest they are—they have abnegated responsibility for managing
those unsupported packages and in doing so have found themselves incapable of
understanding the bind they are in.</p>

<p>This sort of obscuring of fundamental operating principles in the pursuit of
“convenience” is anathema to Arch and is precisely the reason I moved away from
using <code>yaourt</code> (and indeed from using Ubuntu when I jumped from that sinking
ship). Any convenience is purely illusory, in reality it just fosters
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Learned_helplessness" title="Wikipedia entry">learned helplessness</a>.</p>

<p>I understand that the <code>yaourt</code> developer(s) was scratching their own itch, and
this post is not about maligning the project; but there are significant
unintended consequences of giving people a tool that abstracts such a
fundamental element of the distribution away from the user, especially for a
distribution where you are expected to have
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/The_Arch_Way#User-centric" title="The Arch Way">complete control <em>and responsbility</em> over your system</a>.</p>

<p>To be clear, I don't have a complaint with the <em>concept</em> of AUR helpers. I used
<code>yaourt</code> initially before switching to
<a href="http://pbrisbin.com/posts/aurget" title="Patrick Brisbin's AUR helper">aurget</a> and then
alighting on
<a href="https://github.com/falconindy/cower" title="Cower on github">cower</a>, or more particularly,
a partial wrapper for <code>cower</code>:</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><figcaption><span>cowerd </span></figcaption>
 <div class="highlight"><pre><code class='sh'><span class='line'>&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;h1&gt;!/bin/sh&lt;/h1&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;h1&gt;install AUR packages with cower&lt;/h1&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;cd <span class="nv">$HOME</span>/Build &amp;amp;&amp;amp; cower -d <span class="s2">&quot;$1&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">builddir</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;$_&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nb">cd</span> <span class="s2">&quot;$builddir&quot;</span> &amp;amp;&amp;amp; <span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">EDITOR</span><span class="k">:-</span><span class="nv">vi</span><span class="k">}</span> PKGBUILD&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;makepkg -si &amp;amp;&amp;amp; <span class="nb">cd</span> - &amp;amp;&gt;/dev/null&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;read -p <span class="s2">&quot;Remove Build directory? [Y/n]? &quot;</span> yn
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">if</span> <span class="o">[</span> <span class="s2">&quot;$yn&quot;</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s2">&quot;y&quot;</span> <span class="o">]</span>; <span class="k">then</span>&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;printf <span class="s2">&quot;\n%s\n&quot;</span> <span class="s2">&quot;Removing build directory...&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>rm -rf <span class="s2">&quot;$builddir&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;else&lt;/p&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;printf <span class="s2">&quot;%s\n&quot;</span> <span class="s2">&quot;Build completed.&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;p&gt;fi
</span></code></pre></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>This provides me the minimum level of automation I require—essentially only
around downloading and installing a package. It doesn't automatically handle
dependencies, nor manage updating the packages; that remains, rightly in my
view, <em>my</em> responsibility.</p>

<p>If I were to look to a more fully featured wrapper, I would undoubtedly choose
<a href="https://github.com/e36freak/meat" title="meat on Github">meat</a>, however as on my
desktop machine, I only have ~30 AUR packages installed, I don't really need
anything more sophisticated.</p>

<p>So by all means, use an AUR helper. But recognize that it is intended to help
you, not preclude you from being able to accomplish the most simple and
critical task of system maintenance, updating your package manager. Uninstall
<code>yaourt</code> if you are using it and familiarize yourself with <code>makepkg</code>; once you
do understand the relationship between the official repositories and the AUR,
download <code>cower</code> or <code>meat</code>, they are both <em>much</em> better solutions.</p>

<h4>Notes</h4>

<ol>
<li><a href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2009/11/21/dzen2-and-conky-cli-in-dwm/" title="Post from 2009">Myself included</a>…</li>
</ol>


<p>Creative Commons image of crutches by
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/wheatfields/118700600/" title="Flickr CC image">net_efekt on Flickr</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Forking Arch]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2013/03/02/forking/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-02T10:04:00+13:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2013/03/02/forking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/261312/Blog-images/fork.jpg" title="'Fork on Flickr'" >
Over the last couple of months there have been a number of discussions on the Arch boards
about the
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Forum_Etiquette#Arch_Linux_Distribution_Support_ONLY" title="Forum Etiquette">forum policy</a>
of only providing support for Arch Linux, culminating in this
<a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?id=157361" title="Arch Forum thread">long thread about Archbang users</a>
(login required) being denied support and having their threads summarily
closed. As it emerged in the discussion, there seem to be two separate issues
at play here; the question of Arch-derivatives using the Arch brand (logo,
colours and even the forum style sheets), and how the wider community of
GNU/Linux distributions are treated on our boards.</p>

<p>The first issue is relatively simple to address. Allowing derivative
distributions to use the Arch brand is, in my view, a mistake. It dilutes the
value of the Arch “brand” and—as can be seen when people show up having
installed a derivative and thinking they are running Arch—just confuses people.</p>

<p>For some of these derivatives, like Archbang, there is an argument to be made
that once they have completed the installation process, they are in fact
running Arch, albeit an off-the-shelf version. I find this argument to be
specious. All of the derivatives that I have come across, in addition to
“simplifying”<sup>1</sup> the installation process and including <code>X</code> and some
sort of desktop or window manager by default, also make a number of other
system changes that invalidate their claim to being Arch by another name.</p>

<p>See this <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/archlinux/comments/yj2v5/a_new_guibased_version_of_arch_has_gone_live/c5wc6yo" title="Reddit thread on Manjaro Linux">scathing review of Manjaro</a>
or Allan's <a href="http://allanmcrae.com/2012/12/battle-of-the-arch-spin-offs/" title="Allan McRae's blog">roundup of the Arch Spin-Offs</a>
for the details on the decisions these developers make that mean it is not
practicable to support them on the Arch boards, nor desirable to do so in
future. As a distro, Arch is essentially vanilla packages, pacman and rolling
release, and a base on which
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/The_Arch_Way#User-centric" title="The Arch Way">you build your preferred system</a>.
Changing two of those three means that you are not running Arch…</p>

<p>That leads in to the second point, which is I'll paraphrase as “well, we are
all Linux users, so everyone should be welcome to ask for support from Arch
users.” It is a fine sentiment, but one that is neither
<a href="http://www.catb.org/esr/faqs/smart-questions.html#forum" title="ESR's seminal document">historically accurate</a>,
nor in the long term interests of Arch. I have harped on in the past about
<a href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2012/03/17/vampires/" title="My post on the taxonomy of suckers…">help vampires</a>
and last year I came across the perfect illustration of the unchecked effects
of this phenomena:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Right now I'd say the bug queues are flooded with bugs that you can't really act on… It's a strain on the project that there are so many users that don't really get it.</p><footer><strong>Alison Randall</strong> <cite>Ubuntu Technical Architect. Linux Format July 2012</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Your bugtracker becomes essentially unusable. Your forums end up the same way.
No-one ends up getting much in the way of assistance at all, let alone anything
approaching informed help. That may be an inevitable consequence of the
collision between considerable but still finite resources and a philosophy of being
the <acronym title="Operating System">OS</acronym> of the masses; Arch has
nothing like that in terms of resources, and a very different
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/The_Arch_Way" title="The Arch Way, again…">philosophy</a>.</p>

<p>That philosophy doesn't include anything about shortcuts or commoditized images
for a mass user base. It doesn't mention making the installation and
maintenance of your system completely idiot-proof so as to facilitate a
relentless march to the very top of whatever spurious distro popularity ranking
system you subscribe to. And it certainly doesn't say anything about your
entitlement to immediate and courteous support from the Arch community in the
face of your own inability to reach a minimum level of understanding of what it
is that you have installed on your hard drive.</p>

<p>If you think that you can just skip the whole tiresome
<a href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2013/02/08/documentation/" title="Post on documentation">RTFM thing</a>
by downloading a derivative and installing that, how exactly do you expect to be able
to run a rolling release distro that has, on average, a couple of
<a href="https://www.archlinux.org/news/" title="Arch news">significant changes</a> every year?</p>

<p>Sooner or later you are going to have to come to terms with <em>the responsibility</em>
that is an integral part of this type of rolling release and, if you have
installed it yourself, you will be much better placed to be able to build on
that understanding and broaden and deepen your knowledge of your system.</p>

<p>That is ultimately far more satisfying for you, and much more beneficial for
the rest of the community as it means that you will be more able and likely to
contribute back in whatever way that you can; reporting bugs to a functioning
bug tracker, editing the <a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org" title="The finest, actually">fine Wiki</a>,
maintaining packages in <a href="https://aur.archlinux.org" title="Arch User Repository">the AUR</a>,
submitting patches, etc.  Doing all the things that will
sustain Arch and continue to make it an attractive distribution for competent
GNU/Linux users and those that are willing to invest the time to become so.</p>

<h4>Notes</h4>

<ol>
<li>If you have used the Arch install scripts, you would appreciate that it is
not really possible to provide a simpler installation process.</li>
</ol>


<p>Creative Commons licensed image on Flickr by <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/pietroizzo/3514191996/">pietroizzo</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Read The Fine Manual]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2013/02/08/documentation/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-08T19:57:00+13:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2013/02/08/documentation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/261312/Blog-images/documents.jpg" title="'Documents on Flickr'" >
One of the canards about Free and Open Source Software that is peddled by the unscrupulous
marketers of proprietary software is that their product is superior because, among other
things, the scruffy, sandal-wearing Communists that write and distribute their software
for free do not bother to adequately document that software; thereby placing in jeopardy
the business processes in the enterprise that rely on said software to continue to
profitably grease the wheels of the juggernaut of Capitalism.</p>

<p>At heart, it really is an attempt to paint FOSS as a hobbyist's pursuit, unworthy of
consideration by Fortune 500 <acronym title="Chief Inhibiting Officers">CIOs</acronym>
as it is not in the same league as “professional,” proprietary product. This
<acronym title="Fear, Uncertainty & Doubt">FUD</acronym> is not restricted to
the usual suspects; it has also been raised by other, presumably more
<a href="http://www.osnews.com/story/5180" title="Editorial on OS News">objective commentators</a>:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Open Source documentation is terrible. There is no kinder way to put it. Even the commercially distributed software in the Open Source world has substandard documentation. (And believe me, as a technical writer coming from the Windows world, when I tell you that the commercial industrial standards are pretty low). Only a bare handful of Open Source software packages have any documentation at all. And out of the few that do, much of it is either unfinished, inaccurate, or outdated. What counts as explanatory text among geeks would bewilder a nuclear physicist, even a sober one.</p><footer><strong>OSNews Editorial, 2003</strong> <cite><a href='http://www.osnews.com/story/5180'>www.osnews.com/story/5180/&hellip;</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>A more recent survey, published in 2010, identifed the same issue for businesses,
in slightly less histrionic language:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>The No. 1 reason for not choosing open-source solutions was lack of support followed by poor documentation.</p><footer><strong>Zenoss 2010 Survey</strong> <cite><a href='http://gigaom.com/2010/08/11/enterprise-yeah-were-cool-with-open-source/'>gigaom.com/2010/08/11/&hellip;</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>My experience of FOSS documentation, particularly over the last twelve months, has been just the
opposite.</p>

<p>From the middle of 2012 on, I made a couple of significant changes in my computing
environment; I moved from
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/SysVinit" title="Archwiki page…">SysVinit</a>
to <a href="http://freedesktop.org/wiki/Software/systemd" title="Project web page">systemd</a>,
garden variety to
<a href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2013/01/25/uefi/" title="My post on UEFI booting">UEFI booting</a>
and changed my shell from
<a href="http://www.gnu.org/software/bash/" title="GNU Bash page">Bash</a> to
<a href="http://www.zsh.org/" title="Zsh homepage, one of the ugliest on the Web">Zsh</a>.
In each of these cases I found myself having to turn to the documentation the
community has provided in order to understand the implications of the change,
and to familiarise myself with the new tool or approach.</p>

<p>I posted at the time about <a href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2012/08/04/systemd/" title="The Leap to systemd">moving to systemd</a>,
and I don't think—in retrospect—I credited Lennart Poettering enough for the series of posts
he wrote detailing the design decisions and implementation of that system;
those posts (at the time 12, now
<a href="http://0pointer.de/blog/projects" title="Lennart Poettering's blog">grown to 20</a>)
are an impressively thorough, and thoughtful, document of the new init system.</p>

<p>Similarly, when I started reading about <acronym title="Universal Extensible Firmware Interface">UEFI</acronym>
booting, I quickly found myself at <a href="http://www.rodsbooks.com/" title="The author of… Just go there!">Rod Smith's site</a>.
Rod has compiled an exhaustive and authoritative resource on <a href="http://www.rodsbooks.com/gdisk/" title="gdisk page">GPT</a>,
EFI Stub loading and UEFI booting in general. Reading through his clear, approachable
documentation made transitioning to UEFI a much simpler process than, given the
inherent complexity in the ecosystem, I would have thought possible.</p>

<p>Then there is Zsh.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Because zsh contains many features, the zsh manual has been split into a number of sections…</p><footer><strong>zsh manual</strong> <cite><a href='http://linux.die.net/man/1/zsh'>linux.die.net/man/1/zsh/&hellip;</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>And goes it on to list those <em>seventeen</em> sections. If you are not a fan of <code>man</code> pages<sup>1</sup>,
there is the
<a href="http://zsh.sourceforge.net/Doc/Release/zsh_toc.html" title="What it says on the tin…">Zsh Documentation</a>,
the <a href="http://zsh.sourceforge.net/Guide/zshguide.html" title="User's Guide">User's Guide</a> and
<a href="http://zshwiki.org/home/" title="Zsh Wiki">wiki</a>. This amounts to a literally staggering
amount of information—it is no wonder that preconfigured zsh systems like
<a href="http://grml.org/zsh/" title="grml homepage">grml</a> are so popular; they provide
relatively simple ingress to the byzantine ways of this powerful shell.</p>

<p>Finally, also last year, I was privileged to chair the judging for the
<a href="http://www.nzosa.org.nz/" title="NZOSA site">2012 New Zealand Open Source Awards</a>.
This exposed me to the amazing contribution
<a href="http://man7.orgi/mtk.index.html" title="Man pages Michael maintains">Michael Kerrisk</a>
has made to GNU/Linux over the last decade. He is the author, or co-author, of
<em>over 300</em> <code>man</code> pages; and these aren't the glamorous, application pages read
by the masses, but the system pages that document the kernel and <code>glibc</code>
<acronym title="Application Program Interface">APIs</acronym>.</p>

<p>All of this suggests to me that the state of documentation for FOSS is
anything but parlous. At every turn over the last year, when I needed to
be able to refer to documentation for a project, there was a surfeit of it.
And I have only touched on what would normally constitute the primary
sources; there is also all of the other community-driven documentation
around projects, like the
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/" title="The BEST GNU/LINUX wiki on the web">Arch Wiki</a>
or the <a href="http://unix.stackexchange.com/" title="Unix &amp; Linux SE">Stack Exchange sites</a>,
the support available on forums, IRC, blog posts, etc.</p>

<p>Compared to the sterile, mostly out-of-date (and expensive) documentation that
accompanies proprietary software, FOSS is an Alexandrine utopia…</p>

<h4>Notes</h4>

<ol>
<li>And, god knows, <em>I am</em>; <code>man</code> pages are a constant source of knowledge
and delight (and pretty much the only way I can contribute to projects that
I am indebted to).</li>
</ol>


<p>Creative Commons image of documents by
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mwichary/2322639175/">Marcin Wichary</a> on Flickr.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Trolling Arch Linux]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2012/08/18/trolls/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-18T10:47:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2012/08/18/trolls</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/261312/Blog-images/troll.jpg" title="'Troll on Flickr'" >
I posted recently about
<a href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2012/08/04/systemd/" title="Some thoughts on moving across…">my experiences shifting to systemd</a>
and how I found it, for all three of my Arch machines, to be a relatively simple and
straightforward process which, in the intervening weeks, has borne out the views of
the developers and other members of the community who have been using it for a longer
period—it works, and works well. At the start of this week, Stéphane Gaudreault
announced on Arch-dev-public the intention to
<a href="http://mailman.archlinux.org/pipermail/arch-dev-public/2012-August/023389.html" title="ML post seeking developer views">replace the original initscripts with systemd</a>.</p>

<p>The reaction by some to this announcement was, to me, quite disappointing. My view of
open source communities is that by participating you are entering into a social contract.
That contract is that, as you are reliant on the goodwill of the wider community it is
incumbent on you to ensure that your overall contribution—in whatever form—brings
more to the community than it takes away. At the very least, you can strive to ensure
that it is a value neutral exchange.</p>

<p>Sadly, for some of the trolls on the <acronym title="Mailing lists">MLs</acronym>, that
is patently not the case. I want to take a closer look at just one of those threads, for two
reasons. First, it is a textbook case of a particularly pernicious troll. And second, in
conjunction with some other factors, it had an especially damaging effect on the wider
community.</p>

<p>The thread in question is on Arch-general, the largest of the mailing lists. It has
the suitably alarmist title
<a href="http://mailman.archlinux.org/pipermail/arch-general/2012-August/029856.html" title="A trolling we will go…">Think twice before moving to systemd</a>.
The troll, who has had only minimal involvement with the Arch community up until this
unfortunate moment starts by framing his “concern”<sup>1</sup>:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>I just became aware that Arch Linux plans to switch to systemd, and this worries me for several reasons.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Felipe is worried. Ergo, <em>we</em> should be worried. Why should we be worried? Because,
despite the fact that systemd has been discussed and used by Archers since the
<a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?id=96316" title="57 page thread on the Arch BBS">middle of 2010</a>,
it has just come to his attention and now, with the formidable powers of his intellect,
he has detected a disturbance in the force.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>I tried systemd a while ago in a brand new machine with Arch Linux and the boot was <em>much slower</em>. After some exchanges with Lennart Poettering and other people in Google+[1], it became clear I was on my own. Eventually I found the culprit: Fedora uses CONFIG_HZ_1000, and Arch Linux uses CONFIG_HZ_300. It became clear to me that systemd was not ready for prime time, it wasn't thoroughly tested in a lot of machines, and if you have problems Lennart Poettering will blame you (PulseAudio sounds familiar?).</p></blockquote></p>

<p>The salient phrases here are “it became clear I was on my own” and the even more telling,
“it became clear to me that systemd was not ready for prime time.” Once I had managed to
wipe away the tears of gratitude that were coursing down my cheeks, I realized that Arch
finally had finally found what it had been missing for all these years: a saviour. We
were going to be OK after all.</p>

<p>Felipe has “found the culprit.” Despite the best efforts of the Arch developers, upstream,
the other distros that have been using it for considerably longer, and the experience of the
<a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?pid=1147676" title="Thread on systemd - one of many">Arch users reported on our boards</a>,
no-one had the heroic ability to see through to the heart of this conundrum and expose
systemd for the fraud that it is.</p>

<p>But our gratitude should be tempered with some shame for we, the Arch community, have let
Felipe down. We haven't lived up to the standards he expects of us. As he gently admonishes us:
“I was expecting more from the Arch Linux community.” Yes, Felipe, and you were right to.
We let you down; can you forgive us?</p>

<p>The thread goes on to generate more than 50 replies. All of them wasted.
His trolling is not interested in facts, in reason or logic; his method of argumentation is
not rational, and he is not interested in working toward an understanding
of the truth; he just wants to be right. At whatever cost to the wider community. These posts,
and trolls in other fora
<a href="https://lkml.org/lkml/2012/4/12/434" title="LKML exchange with Linus Torvalds">like this one</a>,<sup>2</sup>
are really about gratifying Felipe's own voracious appetite for self-aggrandisement. In reality,
of course, it is a stunning illustration of the
<a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Dunning%E2%80%93Kruger_effect" title="Wikipedia entry">Dunning-Kruger effect</a>.
It would be pathetic if it were a victimless pursuit; but it is not.</p>

<p>Further down in the thread we see the inevitable frustration of the developer who leads
this work for Arch,
<a href="https://www.archlinux.org/developers/#tomegun" title="Tom's developer profile">Tom Gunderson</a>,
finally <a href="http://mailman.archlinux.org/pipermail/arch-general/2012-August/029933.html" title="Tom's reply quoting Linus">boil over</a>.
This precipitates another thread where Tom announces that he will
<a href="http://mailman.archlinux.org/pipermail/arch-general/2012-August/029960.html" title="Tom's mail to the list">no longer participate in this list</a>.
This is from the developer that has patiently and constructively engaged with Arch users on the
list around this issue for the past several months. On his own time.</p>

<p>That is the impact of trolls like Felipe. That is a direct effect of his selfishness on the
wider community. What has he brought to the community? Dissent, distraction and posturing.
What has he taken away? The ability for all of us to engage with one of the developers
of the software we all use. His presence on the list, and that of a few others,
has been nothing short of corrosive.</p>

<p>And as for the smoking gun, the config setting that no-one was smart enough to
discover? Denis A. Altoé Falqueto went to the trouble to build another kernel
and run a test and, contrary to Felipe who provided no such evidence,
<a href="http://mailman.archlinux.org/pipermail/arch-general/2012-August/030145.html" title="Denis' post">posted the results</a>.
You can guess the outcome.</p>

<h4>Notes</h4>

<ol>
<li>See the <a href="http://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=concern+troll">concern troll</a>.</li>
<li>Read the whole thread to fully understand how obstinance can trump reason… See
also his <a href="http://felipec.wordpress.com/2012/05/26/no-mercurial-branches-are-still-not-better-than-git-ones-response-to-jhws-more-on-mercurial-vs-git-with-graphs/">own blog</a>
where he expresses incredulity that his comments on another blog have been deleted.</li>
</ol>


<p>Creative Commons image of the troll on Flickr by
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/56380734@N05/6937763971/">Comrade Foot</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
