<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: community | jasonwryan.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/categories/community/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-08-18T12:49:04+12:00</updated>
  <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jason Ryan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Trolling Arch Linux]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2012/08/18/trolls/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-18T10:47:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2012/08/18/trolls</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/261312/Blog-images/troll.jpg" title="'Troll on Flickr'" >
I posted recently about
<a href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2012/08/04/systemd/" title="Some thoughts on moving across…">my experiences shifting to systemd</a>
and how I found it, for all three of my Arch machines, to be a relatively simple and
straightforward process which, in the intervening weeks, has borne out the views of
the developers and other members of the community who have been using it for a longer
period—it works, and works well. At the start of this week, Stéphane Gaudreault
announced on Arch-dev-public the intention to
<a href="http://mailman.archlinux.org/pipermail/arch-dev-public/2012-August/023389.html" title="ML post seeking developer views">replace the original initscripts with systemd</a>.</p>

<p>The reaction by some to this announcement was, to me, quite disappointing. My view of
open source communities is that by participating you are entering into a social contract.
That contract is that, as you are reliant on the goodwill of the wider community it is
incumbent on you to ensure that your overall contribution—in whatever form—brings
more to the community than it takes away. At the very least, you can strive to ensure
that it is a value neutral exchange.</p>

<p>Sadly, for some of the trolls on the <acronym title="Mailing lists">MLs</acronym>, that
is patently not the case. I want to take a closer look at just one of those threads, for two
reasons. First, it is a textbook case of a particularly pernicious troll. And second, in
conjunction with some other factors, it had an especially damaging effect on the wider
community.</p>

<p>The thread in question is on Arch-general, the largest of the mailing lists. It has
the suitably alarmist title
<a href="http://mailman.archlinux.org/pipermail/arch-general/2012-August/029856.html" title="A trolling we will go…">Think twice before moving to systemd</a>.
The troll, who has had only minimal involvement with the Arch community up until this
unfortunate moment starts by framing his “concern”<sup>1</sup>:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>I just became aware that Arch Linux plans to switch to systemd, and this worries me for several reasons.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Felipe is worried. Ergo, <em>we</em> should be worried. Why should we be worried? Because,
despite the fact that systemd has been discussed and used by Archers since the
<a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?id=96316" title="57 page thread on the Arch BBS">middle of 2010</a>,
it has just come to his attention and now, with the formidable powers of his intellect,
he has detected a disturbance in the force.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>I tried systemd a while ago in a brand new machine with Arch Linux and the boot was <em>much slower</em>. After some exchanges with Lennart Poettering and other people in Google+[1], it became clear I was on my own. Eventually I found the culprit: Fedora uses CONFIG_HZ_1000, and Arch Linux uses CONFIG_HZ_300. It became clear to me that systemd was not ready for prime time, it wasn't thoroughly tested in a lot of machines, and if you have problems Lennart Poettering will blame you (PulseAudio sounds familiar?).</p></blockquote></p>

<p>The salient phrases here are “it became clear I was on my own” and the even more telling,
“it became clear to me that systemd was not ready for prime time.” Once I had managed to
wipe away the tears of gratitude that were coursing down my cheeks, I realized that Arch
finally had finally found what it had been missing for all these years: a saviour. We
were going to be OK after all.</p>

<p>Felipe has “found the culprit.” Despite the best efforts of the Arch developers, upstream,
the other distros that have been using it for considerably longer, and the experience of the
<a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?pid=1147676" title="Thread on systemd - one of many">Arch users reported on our boards</a>,
no-one had the heroic ability to see through to the heart of this conundrum and expose
systemd for the fraud that it is.</p>

<p>But our gratitude should be tempered with some shame for we, the Arch community, have let
Felipe down. We haven't lived up to the standards he expects of us. As he gently admonishes us:
“I was expecting more from the Arch Linux community.” Yes, Felipe, and you were right to.
We let you down; can you forgive us?</p>

<p>The thread goes on to generate more than 50 replies. All of them wasted.
His trolling is not interested in facts, in reason or logic; his method of argumentation is
not rational, and he is not interested in working toward an understanding
of the truth; he just wants to be right. At whatever cost to the wider community. These posts,
and trolls in other fora
<a href="https://lkml.org/lkml/2012/4/12/434" title="LKML exchange with Linus Torvalds">like this one</a>,<sup>2</sup>
are really about gratifying Felipe's own voracious appetite for self-aggrandisement. In reality,
of course, it is a stunning illustration of the
<a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Dunning%E2%80%93Kruger_effect" title="Wikipedia entry">Dunning-Kruger effect</a>.
It would be pathetic if it were a victimless pursuit; but it is not.</p>

<p>Further down in the thread we see the inevitable frustration of the developer who leads
this work for Arch,
<a href="https://www.archlinux.org/developers/#tomegun" title="Tom's developer profile">Tom Gunderson</a>,
finally <a href="http://mailman.archlinux.org/pipermail/arch-general/2012-August/029933.html" title="Tom's reply quoting Linus">boil over</a>.
This precipitates another thread where Tom announces that he will
<a href="http://mailman.archlinux.org/pipermail/arch-general/2012-August/029960.html" title="Tom's mail to the list">no longer participate in this list</a>.
This is from the developer that has patiently and constructively engaged with Arch users on the
list around this issue for the past several months. On his own time.</p>

<p>That is the impact of trolls like Felipe. That is a direct effect of his selfishness on the
wider community. What has he brought to the community? Dissent, distraction and posturing.
What has he taken away? The ability for all of us to engage with one of the developers
of the software we all use. His presence on the list, and that of a few others,
has been nothing short of corrosive.</p>

<p>And as for the smoking gun, the config setting that no-one was smart enough to
discover? Denis A. Altoé Falqueto went to the trouble to build another kernel
and run a test and, contrary to Felipe who provided no such evidence,
<a href="http://mailman.archlinux.org/pipermail/arch-general/2012-August/030145.html" title="Denni's post">posted the results</a>.
You can guess the outcome.</p>

<h4>Notes</h4>

<ol>
<li>See the <a href="http://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=concern+troll">concern troll</a>.</li>
<li>Read the whole thread to fully understand how obstinance can trump reason… See
also his <a href="http://felipec.wordpress.com/2012/05/26/no-mercurial-branches-are-still-not-better-than-git-ones-response-to-jhws-more-on-mercurial-vs-git-with-graphs/">own blog</a>
where he expresses incredulity that his comments on another blog have been deleted.</li>
</ol>


<p>Creative Commons image of the troll on Flickr by
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/56380734@N05/6937763971/">Comrade Foot</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Leap to systemd]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2012/08/04/systemd/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-04T09:32:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2012/08/04/systemd</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/261312/Blog-images/leap.jpg" title="Leap image on Flickr" >
I posted a couple of weeks ago about the impact of some of the current
<a href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2012/07/19/breakage/" title="Post on the glibc change">changes to Arch Linux</a>.
There seems to be quite a bit of it about, because in conjunction with the move from
<span class="file">/lib</span> to <span class="file">/usr/lib</span>—and motivated by the same
overarching shifts in the other distributions—the other major change making its way through
the Arch community is the move to
<a href="http://freedesktop.org/wiki/Software/systemd" title="Project page">systemd</a>. This change, however, has
been more controversial because it marks a shift away from Arch's central configuration
file, <a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Rc.conf" title="Arch wiki entry on rc.conf">/etc/rc.conf</a>;
a move that has disconcerted a number of people.</p>

<p>I'm not going to get into whether or not this move is consistent with
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/The_Arch_Way" title="Wiki entry">The Arch Way</a>, because that has
been thrashed over extensively on the
<a href="http://mailman.archlinux.org/pipermail/arch-dev-public/2012-July/023283.html" title="ML thread on rc.conf">mailing</a>
<a href="http://mailman.archlinux.org/pipermail/arch-dev-public/2012-July/023258.html" title="And another one…">lists</a>,
but also—and more importantly—because Arch is a rolling release, which means change is <em>inevitable</em>.
What is more, after watching all the back and forth on the <acronym title="Mailing lists">ML</acronym>
and on the <a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?id=96316&amp;p=1" title="Arch BBS thread on systemd">boards</a>, I am convinced that the
<a href="http://www.archlinux.org/developers/#tomegun" title="Tom Gunderson">developer overseeing this shift</a>
both knows what he is doing and is acting in the best interests of Arch.</p>

<p>This view has been validated by my experience of shifting to systemd on my machines.</p>

<p>When the new initscripts package was pushed to [testing] in the middle of last month,
I stripped out all of the redundant options in <span class="file">/etc/rc.conf</span>
and took the ten minutes or so to read about and then create the new files. I then spent some
time reading up on systemd, principally
<a href="http://0pointer.de/blog/projects/systemd-for-admins-1.html" title="One of TWELVE…">Lennart Poettering's series of posts</a>,
the <a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Systemd" title="Good, but needing some structure">Arch wiki entry</a>
and the many and various
<a href="http://0pointer.de/public/systemd-man/" title="One for everything">manual pages</a>.</p>

<p>Over the last couple of days, I have migrated all of my machines over to systemd. I found it
to be a very straightforward process. I went for a pure systemd approach, for reasons I will
return to. Essentially, this is how I tackled it.</p>

<p>First, for each machine, I established what daemons were running. I did this by using
<a href="http://pikacode.com/jasonwryan/Veles/file/default/Scripts/daemons.sh" title="Pretty sure it is one of Xyne's">this shell script</a>
and cross checking entries in my <span class="file">/etc/rc.conf</span>. Then
it was just a matter of installing systemd:<sup>1</sup></p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><pre><code class='sh'><span class='line'>sudo pacman -S systemd systemd-sysvcompat systemd-arch-units
</span></code></pre></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>The only outstanding file to be created was <span class="file">/etc/timezone</span>, the
others—all documented in <code>man rc.conf</code>—I had created earlier in the month. Then, with the
list of the services I would need running on each box, I enabled them. I think it is
fair to say that the only thing that is clunky about systemd is the command syntax for
managing units. Repeatedly typing <code>systemctl enable foo.service</code> is as tedious as it is
error prone, so I hacked up a
<a href="http://pikacode.com/jasonwryan/Centurion/file/default/Scripts/sysd" title="sysd - *so* much easier">wrapper script</a>:</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><pre><code class='sh'><span class='line'>sysd <span class="nb">enable </span>acpid
</span><span class='line'>sysd <span class="nb">enable </span>lvm
</span><span class='line'>etc…
</span></code></pre></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>I also activated some additional gettys, as I like to log into a tmux session in TTY2 when
I don't need or want to start <code>X</code>:</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><pre><code class='sh'><span class='line'>ln -sf /usr/lib/systemd/system/getty@.service /etc/systemd/system/getty.target.wants/getty@tty2.service
</span></code></pre></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>And I misguidedly wrote a couple of custom service files that turned out to be
<a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?id=146207" title="BBS post on said files">completely unnecessary</a>;
and then I was done.</p>

<p>On all three boxes I rebooted and that was it. The only issue I experienced was
the final shutdown after removing initscripts and before booting up with
systemd. After issuing <code>shutdown -r now</code> the process
hung with a message about a missing <span class="file">inittab</span> file.
In retrospect, I should have added <code>init=/bin/systemd</code> to my kernel parameters
and not unistalled instiscripts until I had booted with systemd. This has
now been added to the
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Systemd" title="Archwiki systemd page">systemd wiki page</a>.</p>

<p>Overall, though: no real drama, just a blur of text<sup>2</sup> and then the
login prompt. While I haven't seen a dramatic decrease in boot time,
booting does <em>feel</em> a bit snappier and two of my three machines shutdown
markedly more quickly. Consider me sold.</p>

<p>That brings me back to the decision to opt for a pure systemd approach, rather than
hanging on to a completely eviscerated <span class="file">/etc/rc.conf</span>. The
Arch community has been told that the intention is to
<a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?pid=1133957#p1133957" title="BBS post by tomegun">support the rc.conf format forever</a>;
I can't help but think this is a mistake. In the same way that
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Pacman#Partial_upgrades_are_unsupported" title="Pacman entry on Arch Wiki">partial upgrades are unsupported</a>,
I think that systemd is Arch's inevitable future and the community should be encouraged to accept that, <code>Syu</code> and
move on…</p>

<p>Having said that, I appreciate the consideration shown by the developers in wanting to assure
people that their choice would continue to be catered for; and perhaps, over time, people still
using initscripts will be regarded with the same sense of wry amusement as those who still show
up from time to time with <code>hal</code> in their <code>DAEMONS</code> line.</p>

<h3>Update 4/8/12</h3>

<p>Tom Gunderson, the developer who looks after this part of Arch, has clarified the
comment about the long term support for initscripts. As comments are hosted on
a third-party paltform, I thought that it should be included in the body of the
post.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Just a clarification: regarding the (probably very unwise) promise of "supporting &lt;span="file">rc.conf</span> forever", the intended meaning was that initscripts will support the syntax, not that initscripts themselves will always stay around (nor that systemd will gain support for the syntax in case initscripts is dropped).</p></p><p><p>At the moment systemd <strong>does</strong> support <span class="file">rc.conf</span> (when installed in conjunction with initscripts), but this is meant as a transitional measure only, and will likely go away eventually (though probably not soon).</p></blockquote></p>

<h4>Notes</h4>

<ol>
<li>Note this approach will <em>remove</em> sysvinit and initscripts and <code>mv /etc/rc.conf{,.pacsave}</code>.</li>
<li>Make sure you remove <code>quiet</code> from your kernel parameters for your first systemd
boot so you can see that everything starts correctly…</li>
</ol>


<p>Creative commons image on Flickr by
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sovietuk/486119799/" title="leap by rick harrison">Tricky</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Myth of Breakage]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2012/07/19/breakage/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-19T19:23:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2012/07/19/breakage</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="https://dl.dropbox.com/u/261312/Blog-images/broken.jpg" title="Image of breakage on Flickr" >
Breakage is one of the memes of the Arch Linux community; it is referenced frequently on the
<a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/" title="Arch Linux BBS">Arch boards</a> and in the various
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/IRC_Channels" title="Wiki page listing channels">IRC channels</a>.
It doesn't take newcomers long to realize that, whether something is actually broken or not,
there is always
<a href="http://allanmcrae.com/category/arch-linux/" title="Allan's Blog">someone they can blame</a>.<sup>1</sup></p>

<p>My experience of Arch, over the last three and a bit years, is quite the opposite. I have yet to
experience anything that would qualify as breakage. Sure, there have been bugs, mostly upstream,
and the more frequent moments where I haven't been as diligent as I should, but not once have I
had a machine that was unbootable or otherwise unusable. Arch has, on both my home and work
machines, been incredibly stable and reliable.</p>

<p>For a number of Arch Linux users, however, that was not their experience over the last week when
<a href="http://www.archlinux.org/news/the-lib-directory-becomes-a-symlink/" title="News item on the move">/lib was moved to /usr/lib</a>.
The volume of people on the boards and on IRC reporting unbootable or unusable systems was
remarkable. Remarkable because, despite the fact that the
<a href="http://www.archlinux.org/news/the-lib-directory-becomes-a-symlink/" title="Once more, just in case…">news item</a>, the
<a href="http://www.archlinux.org/news/the-lib-directory-becomes-a-symlink/" title="Arch wiki page on the change">wiki page</a>,
and the <a href="http://mailman.archlinux.org/pipermail/arch-announce/2012-July/000317.html" title="Mail archive">email to arch-announce</a>
all <em>explicitly</em> warned people not to use the <code>--force</code> option,<sup>2</sup> so many did.</p>

<p><span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='90% of the breakage was because people either didn&#8217;t see, or disregarded, that advice. '>
Sadly, these red-boxed warnings were apparently not enough.
90% of the breakage was because people either didn't see, or disregarded, that advice.
The remaining 10% were either in a hurry and didn't pay close attention to how
to deal with any leftover files in <span class="file">/lib</span> or <code>rm -rf</code>'ed
in the wrong directory.
<a href="http://www.gnu.org/fun/jokes/shit-happens.html" title="GNU Humour…">Accidents happen</a>.
</span></p>

<p>What I am interested in is the people who fell into the much larger category,
and principally those that didn't see any of the communications about this
change in advance of updating and reasoned, based on a recent change that did
<a href="http://www.archlinux.org/news/filesystem-upgrade-manual-intervention-required-1/" title="News item on filesystem upgrade">require the use of --force</a>,
that this was the most expedient way to resolve <code>pacman</code> reporting conflicting
files.</p>

<p>Some context. The <code>glibc</code> update was released to the
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Testing#.5Btesting.5D" title="Wiki entry on Testing">[testing] repository</a>
in the first week of July: and there were a couple of long threads<sup>3</sup>
about issues and fixes before it was pushed to [core]. By the time the
package was released for general consumption, it had been tested and the
developers had obviously planned how to make what is a fundamental system
change with a minimal amount of user intervention.  I think that, given the
magnitude of the challenge, they did a superb job.</p>

<p>How then did it go so wrong for so many?<sup>4</sup> To answer that, you have
to consider the nature of Arch. It's <em>not</em> the sort of distribution where you
install it and then just go on your merry way, installing
<a href="http://oswatershed.org/" title="It's SCIENCE, Jim">the least obsolete packages</a>,
revelling in the speed of the package manager and generally being
a 1337 h@x0r…</p>

<p>Successfully running a rolling release like Arch, irrespective of your level of
competence, means staying in touch with what is happening—in
<a href="http://kmkeen.com/pacmatic/" title="Pacman wrapper that pulls news updates">some form or other</a>.
Subscribing to the arch-general <acronym title="Mailing list">ML</acronym>,
visiting the forums, idling in IRC; somehow remaining connected to what is
going on in the community so that you don't blindly update one day and wonder
why your system is broken.</p>

<p>This strikes me as a real strength; by design Arch encourages its users to
participate in the community. Even if you are only lurking, over time you will
inevitably find yourself posting in a thread, responding to an email, editing
the wiki,
<a href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2012/03/09/aurphan/" title="Post on aurphan">adopting an orphaned package</a>—increasingly
getting involved and contributing.</p>

<p>This level of involvement is not for everyone. Some may find it onerous or
a waste of their time. That's fine. There are any number of other distros
that do not ask for this level of commitment. The <em>quid pro quo</em> for
running Arch, though, is that you are prepared, in whatever shape or form
best works for you, to give something back; at the very least, that is your
attention.</p>

<h4>Notes</h4>

<ol>
<li>This is, of course, a reference to said Arch meme: Allan is one
of the developers who has contributed an enormous amount to Arch and the fact
that his IRC nick is <code>allanbrokeit</code> is purely coincidental.</li>
<li>At the end of 2011, the short option <code>-f</code>
<a href="http://mailman.archlinux.org/pipermail/pacman-dev/2011-October/014589.html" title="Post to ML anouncing change">was removed</a>
from <code>pacman</code> so “it at least makes people read the word 'force' and maybe they
will have some sense to step back and think about what they are doing first.”</li>
<li><a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?id=144620">https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?id=144620</a> and
<a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?id=144616">https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewtopic.php?id=144616</a></li>
<li>Relatively speaking. In situations like this, the overwhelming amount of traffic
is about what went wrong, not people posting to say they had no difficulties whatsoever…</li>
</ol>


<p>Creative Commons image on Flickr from
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/daviddoctorrose/431786001/" title="Broken keyboard on Flickr">djeucalyptus</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Misunderstanding Arch]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2012/06/16/misunderstanding/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-16T10:52:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2012/06/16/misunderstanding</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/261312/Blog-images/hands.jpg" title="'mutt logo'" ></p>

<p>I am frequently struck by how many people arrive on the
<a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/" title="Arch Linux Forums">Arch boards</a> without <em>any</em>
understanding of how Arch is different from the other GNU/Linux communities
they may have spent time with (if, indeed, they have spent any time in
another community before trying Arch). For me, this is akin to arriving in a
foreign country and not bothering to familiarize yourself at all with the local
mores and customs; it lies on a spectrum somewhere between ignorance and
outright arrogance.</p>

<p>The result, inevitably, is that these people are shocked
when their expectations of how they <em>should</em> be treated are at odds with the
reception their behaviour invites…</p>

<p>Before venturing any further, I should preface my remarks about this with
something of a disclaimer. These are my own views and not those of the current,
or past, forum staff.</p>

<p>One of Arch's significant acheivements is the quality of
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org" title="THE best GNU/Linux Wiki">its documentation</a>.
Not just the technical documentation describing how to install and configure
Arch, but the cultural documentation that sets out
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/The_Arch_Way" title="The Arch Way">Arch's philosophy</a>
and <a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Forum_Etiquette" title="Forum Etiquette">standards of behaviour</a>. Both these pages provide clear statements on what to expect when
using Arch Linux and a clear indication of how to respectfully interact with the
community when you are seeking help.</p>

<p>The defining statement about Arch's intended user base is quite direct and
unambiguous:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Arch Linux targets and accommodates competent GNU/Linux users<br/>by giving them complete control and responsibility over the system.</p><footer><strong>The Arch Way</strong> <cite><a href='https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/The_Arch_Way#User-centric'>wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/&hellip;</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>The expression “targets and accommodates” doesn't exclude other users—for
example, those that are not necessarily competent, but are wanting to learn
more about the specifics of how their machines work—it does, however, signal
quite explicitly what sort of community Arch is. And what it is not.</p>

<p><a href="http://ubuntu.com" title="Ubuntu Linux">Ubuntu</a> is an excellent distribution. Like Arch,
it has very specific aims and a clear concept of what the Ubuntu community is.
Popularity is central to Ubuntu's culture. People coming from Ubuntu, who
haven't bothered to familiarize themselves with Arch's values, often struggle
to appreciate the difference; leading to comments like this one:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Maybe if Arch is friendly and Arch forum is friendly, it might go some<br/>place, who knows…</p><footer><strong>Linux Journal commenter</strong> <cite><a href='http://www.linuxjournal.com/content/arch-way#comment-361974'>www.linuxjournal.com/content/&hellip;</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>This was posted in reply to a post on Arch in which the author noted how to
seek help with Arch Linux:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>You'll find far less hand-holding on the Arch Forums than some of the other<br/>distro's forums, and for good reason.  Arch has one of the most informative,<br/>user-friendly wiki's out there. Do not, I repeat, DO NOT ask a question in the<br/>forums or on IRC without searching the wiki and the forums first.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Similarly, looking through the threads in
<a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/viewforum.php?id=23" title="Newbie board">Newbie Corner</a>
will periodically turn up new posters who are indignant at being told to
<acronym title="Read The Fscking Manual">RTFM</acronym> and see it as some
sort of <em>personal</em> attack, when in fact it is just someone pointing out the
obvious to them. The community hasn't compiled all that documentation just
so they can sit around and regurgitate answers for people who are either
unwilling or incapable of making the minimum amount of  effort required to
solve their own problems…</p>

<p>If you want handholding, there are plenty of online communities that will
cater for you. If you install Arch and think that you are automatically entitled
to immediate support for issues that you encounter, then you are mistaken.
If you think that Arch will suffer if you don't get what you want, then
your problems extend significantly beyond your choice of distro.</p>

<p>The community has worked hard over the years to keep the signal-to-noise ratio
on the boards high, that way, the forums remain a helpful resource for the community,
not a breeding ground for
<a href="http://jasonwryan.com/blog/2012/03/17/vampires/" title="Post on parasites…">help vampires</a>.</p>

<h4>Notes</h4>

<p>Flickr Creative Commons image by
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/angellic/47031159/">si_si_ay</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Taxonomy of Help Vampires]]></title>
    <link href="http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2012/03/17/vampires/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-17T16:25:00+13:00</updated>
    <id>http://jasonwryan.github.com/blog/2012/03/17/vampires</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/261312/Blog-images/vampire1.jpg" alt="image" /></p>

<p>If you have spent any time at all amongst online (or, for that matter,
off-line) communities, you will be familiar with the help vampire. If,
by some combination of fortune and ignorance, you haven’t come across
this term before, read Amy Hoy’s original—and definitive—
<a href="http://slash7.com/2006/12/22/vampires/" title="Amy's blog on help vampires">post on this scourge</a>,
<em>now</em>.</p>

<p>Amy has some excellent tips on identifying help vampires, however, since
she originally shed some sunlight on this odious species, they have
become even more cunning and have adapted; to the point where there are
now several varieties that you should be wary of if you are determined
to prevent your online community from becoming overrun with them.</p>

<p><strong>The Infant</strong> The easiest to spot because, due to their nascent form,
they have not developed sophisticated anti-detection strategies as yet.
Also, encouragingly, these are the most likely to respond to the
corrective measures Amy outlines in her post.</p>

<p>The infant has probably learned their dependant ways in some other
online community with a higher tolerance for their spoonfeeding needs.
Corrective measures, vigorously and repeatedly applied <em>can</em> turn them
around; but even small amounts of reinforcement of this behaviour can
quickly see them morph into one of the more sinister types…</p>

<p><img src="http://media.tumblr.com/tumblr_m10ce18Jda1qz8s9s.jpg" alt="image" /></p>

<p><strong>The Leech</strong> This reprehensible lifeform just sucks and sucks and
<em>sucks</em> until there is nothing left. Some of their forum threads may
even appear reasonable, but looking at their profile in totality tells a
shocking story. All of their posts are in their own threads, they are
not interested in helping anyone else with a problem. They will move
remorselessly from issue to issue, expecting the community to provide
answers for them at a hemorrhagic rate.</p>

<p>They won’t have made any edits to
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org" title="The BEST godamn GNU/Linux wiki on the web">the Wiki</a>,
no matter how trivial. They won’t
<a href="https://aur.archlinux.org" title="Arch User repository">maintain any packages</a> or donate
any time or
<a href="http://www.archlinux.org/donate/" title="Donate now and recieve a FREE package update!">money</a>
to your community. But they will be there night after night, posting
their problems and waiting for the hapless to expend their time and
energy on them. Like all parasites, they will adapt over time so remain
vigilant.</p>

<p><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/261312/Blog-images/vampire3.jpg" alt="image" /></p>

<p><strong>The Fanger</strong> The out-and-out help vampire, unabashed and unashamed of
their <em>needs</em>. Their sense of entitlement will be telegraphed by needy
and demanding thread titles, often featuring exhortations like “HELP”
and “URGENT” and almost always embellished with a liberal—and, at times
of “real crises,” exclusive—use of all caps and exclamation marks.</p>

<p>The Fanger will also occasionally table (sadly, almost inevitably empty)
threats about leaving your community and going off to use some other
software; as if the dependency relationship is somehow reversed and it
is you, the community, that will suffer if they leave.</p>

<p>The other classic trait of the hardcore vampire is that, like their
fictional avatars, they see nothing when a mirror is held up to them.
You can call their behaviour as much as you like, it will have no
effect. Your only solution here is technology:
<a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2011/06/suspension-ban-or-hellban.html" title="Coding Horror on the Hell Ban">the hell ban</a>.</p>

<hr />

<p>The Arch Linux community has grown considerably since it emerged
<a href="http://www.archlinux.org/news/arch-linux-turns-10/" title="w00t!">ten years ago this month</a>. Over
the last couple of years, the forums in particular have seen a lot of
new users signing up to participate. This is unquestionably a good
thing™</p>

<p>However, Arch is clearly labelled as being for
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/The_Arch_Way#User-centric" title="The Arch Way: user-centric">competent users</a>
(and here competent can equally mean accomplished – or prepared to
invest in themselves and the community to become competent) and that
means not enabling these sorts of vampiric behaviours, in whatever form
they manifest.</p>

<h5>Notes</h5>

<p>Photography is all Creative Commons licensed on Flickr by, in order of
appearance:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/randaldroher/2161723492/" title="The Count, by Randall Drohrer on Flickr">Randall Drohrer</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/phatcontroller/2620032517" title="Leech, by phatcontroler on Flickr">phatcontroller</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sandrafalkevik/4465039571" title="Vampire, by Sandra Falkevik on Flickr">Sandra Falkevik</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
